Good evening, everyone
大家晚上好
No, but it's indeed over venture
不 但确实是过度冒险了
The brevets are swim Priatelli ma on eco a messada ne resume you koi
（法语）
So the translation good evening to all our families complete translation, yeah, please
所以请翻译一下 祝我们所有的家人晚上好 请完整地翻译
Yep, so good evening to everyone to all my comrades who don't understand me fuck them
是的 所以对所有人说晚上好 对那些不理解我的同志们 去他的
Is it a correct translation?
这是正确的翻译吗
So, what can I say?
那么 我能说什么呢
Welcome to the sixth Soverzi festival and thanks for being with us for six years.
欢迎来到第六届Soverzi节 感谢大家六年来一直与我们同在
Thanks for everyone in this hall for being with us or to the new people.
感谢在座的每一位 感谢新来的朋友们
Thanks again.
再次感谢
There is no need to present Slavo into detail, but I
没必要详细介绍斯拉沃热 但是我应该提一下 在他访问克罗地亚期间 又出版了两本书
The first one is published by Meander.
第一本是由Meander出版的
It's Gledanij's Cosa.
它是《Gledanij的Cosa》
And the second one is The Year of Jimic Dangerously, published by Fractura.
第二本是由Fractura出版的《Jimic危险的一年》
But the topic of today's lecture is, I think for all of you, much more interesting.
但是今天讲座的主题 我认为对你们所有人来说 更加有趣
It's called Love as a Political Category.
它被称为“作为一种政治范畴的爱”
I remember when I was trying to convince Slava in Ljubljana to take this topic, he was first, no, no, no, what can I say about love?
我记得当我在卢布尔雅那试图说服斯拉沃热采取这个主题时 他起初是拒绝的 不 不 不 我能说什么关于爱
And then in the end, I got a mail a few weeks later and he said, okay, I will do this lecture.
然后几周后 我收到了一封邮件 他说 好吧 我将做这个讲座
So, let's see.
所以 让我们看看
A big applause for Slava.
为斯拉沃热热烈鼓掌
Oh my goodness.
哦 我的天哪
I hope you will not be disappointed because this time I will not do with any political interventions, it will really be about the concept of love, how can it be used politically.
我希望你们不会失望 因为这次我不会进行任何政治干预 这真的会关于爱的概念 它如何可以在政治上被使用
First, a quote, if all else perished and he remained, I should still continue to be.
首先 一个引用 如果其他一切都消失了而他仍然存在 我仍然会继续存在 如果其他一切都存在而他被湮灭了
the universe would turn to a mighty stranger.
整个宇宙也就变成了一个巨大的陌生人 我不会觉得自己是它的一部分 引用结束 （译注：电影翻译 如果你还在这个世界存在着 那么无论变成什么样 对我来说都有意义 如果你不在了 无论这个世界多么美好 对我来说都是一片荒芜 我就是一个孤魂野鬼 ）
This is how in Emily Bronte's Withering Hates,
这是在艾米莉·勃朗特的《呼啸山庄》中 凯蒂如何描述她与希斯克利夫的关系 并提供了无条件的情爱的简洁定义
There is an unmistakable dimension of terror at work here.
这里明显存在恐怖的维度
Think about the ecstatic trance of Tristan and Isolde, ready to obliterate the entire social reality in their immersion into the night of deadly enjoyment.
想想特里斯坦和伊索尔德的欣喜若狂的恍惚状态 准备在沉浸在致命享受的夜晚中的时候 抹去整个社会现实 （译注：这句话引用了著名的中世纪爱情故事特里斯坦和伊索尔德（Tristan and Isolde）的情节 探讨了两位主人公陷入狂喜恍惚状态的主题 在这种状态下 他们愿意为了沉浸在彼此的爱中而忽略整个社会现实 即使这种爱带来的是致命的享受 ）
Now, I could go on here about erotic love because I sincerely think that in contrast to our youth, the youth of those who are already old here,
现在 我可以在这里继续谈论情爱 因为我真诚地认为 与我们年轻时相比 我们这些已经老去的人的青春
when you know to fight for sexual freedom was experienced as liberating and even monogamous love was considered or dismissed as a bourgeois convention and so on, I think that today more and more love,
当你知道为性自由而战被认为是解放的 甚至一夫一妻制爱情被视为或被轻视为资产阶级的惯例等 我认为今天越来越多的爱 单纯热烈的爱正浮现为某种危险且确切的颠覆性事物
Think about how you are addressed in your everyday life by society, what society demands of you.
想想社会如何在你的日常生活中对你发出指令 社会对你的要求是什么
It's basically a kind of slightly spiritual pseudo-Buddhist hedonism.
基本上是一种略带灵性的伪佛教享乐主义
Ideology is telling you, be faithful to yourself, realize your true potentials and experiment with your life.
意识形态告诉你 忠于自己 实现你的真正潜力 并对你的生活进行尝试
Try all different options.
尝试所有不同的选择
Don't fixate yourself on certain stable identities.
不要将自己固定在某些稳定的身份上
Life is dynamic, fluid, and so on and so on.
生活是动态的 流动的 等等
And I claim within this economy, not only is stable love, passionate love,
我声称 在这种经济体系中 不仅稳定的爱情、热情的爱情
emerging as an obstacle to your authentic development but even the crucial dimension of love is gradually disappearing.
成为了你真实发展的障碍 甚至爱的关键维度也在逐渐消失
What is love?
什么是爱
As Alain Badiou, our good friend who wasn't able to come here, put it in his wonderful book In praise of love.
正如我们的好朋友阿兰·巴迪欧 他没能来到这里 在他的精彩书籍《赞美爱情》中所说
There is always something traumatic, extremely violent in love.
爱中必定有创伤性的、极度暴力的成分
Love is a permanent emergency state.
爱是一种永久的紧急状态、突发情况
You fall in love and it's crucial that in English and in French we use this expression, to fall in love.
你坠入爱河 英语和法语中我们使用这个表达 坠入爱河 是至关重要的
You lose control.
你失去了控制
It's really, I claim that love, the experience of passionate love, is the most elementary metaphysical experience it's a platonic experience,
我声称 热情的爱情经验是最基本的形而上学经验 它是一种柏拉图式的经验
in the sense of you lead your easy daily life you meet friends you go to parties whatever everything is normal maybe here and there wine nightstand but whatever
这意味着你过着轻松的日常生活 遇见朋友 参加派对 一切都很正常 或许偶尔一夜情 但无所谓
and then you passionately fall in love everything is ruined the entire balance of your life is lost
然后你热情地坠入爱河 一切都毁了 你生活的整个平衡都被打破了 一切都服从于这一个人
everything is subordinated to this one person I almost cannot imagine in normal daily life outside war and so on
除了战争外 我几乎无法想象在正常的日常生活中还有什么比爱情更暴力的经历 我认为这就是为什么现在所以受欢迎的“导师”都在试图精确地驯服或抹去爱的过度
it's as if love is too poisonous and then they tell you you know that The trick that they try to offer you, all the marriage agencies, dating agencies, is how to find yourself in love without falling in love.
就好像爱太有毒了 然后他们告诉你 你知道他们试图提供给你的技巧 所有的婚姻机构、约会机构 都是如何在不坠入爱河的情况下找到爱情
This idea came to me when on one of the transatlantic flights I was in a, I read one of those stupid airline journals and there was a big text there claiming publicity,
这个想法是我在一次横越大西洋的航班上得到的 我读了一本那些愚蠢的航空杂志 里面有一篇大文章声称 我们将使你能够在不坠入爱河、不暴露于这种危险中的情况下找到爱情
And I think this fits perfectly our daily narcissistic metaphysics.
我认为这完美契合了我们日常的自恋形而上学
You know the old story that I repeat all the time.
你知道我一直重复的老故事
We want coffee without caffeine, we want beer without alcohol, and we want love without its dangerous moment where you get lost.
我们想要无咖啡因的咖啡 无酒精的啤酒 以及没有危险时刻你会迷失的爱情
But okay, enough of this.
但好吧 这些就够了
Now this is Eros, erotic love.
现在这是厄洛斯（译注：希腊神话中的爱与情欲之神） 情欲之爱
Then we have its counterpoint in Christianity, agape.
然后我们有它在基督教中的对位 即神之爱
Agape functions in a wholly different way, how?
神之爱的运作方式完全不同 怎么不同呢
It may appear that in contrast to Eros, with its violent subtraction from the collective space, the love for a collective succeeds in getting rid of the excess of terrorizing violence.
看起来 与情欲之爱相比 情欲之爱对集体空间进行了暴力削减（译注：陷入情欲之爱的双方眼中只有对方 而没有社会中的其余各人） 神之爱通过对集体的爱而成功地摆脱了过度的恐怖暴力
Does agape not imply an emphatic yes to the beloved collective, ultimately to the entire humanity, or even, as in Buddhism, to the entire domain of suffering life?
难道神之爱不意味着对所爱的集体的强烈肯定 最终对整个人类 或者像在佛教中 对整个苦难生命的领域的肯定吗
The first counterargument is provided here by the reply to a simple question.
第一个反论点在这里由对一个简单问题的回答提供
Just think about it.
想想看
Which political regimes in the 20th century legitimized their power by evoking the subject's love for their leader.
哪些20世纪的政治制度通过唤起民众对他们领袖的爱来合法化他们的权力
It was the so-called, I don't like the term, totalitarian ones.
那就是所谓的 我不喜欢这个术语 极权主义的
Today, remember, it is only and precisely North Korean regime which evokes all the time the infinite love of the Korean people for Kim Il-sung, Kim Yong-il, and so on,
今天 记住 只有并且确切地是朝鲜政权 一直在唤起朝鲜人民对金日成、金正日等的无限爱
and vice versa, the radiating love of the leader for his people, love expressed in continuous acts of grace.
反之亦然 领导人对他的人民的辐射式的爱 通过持续的恩典行为表达
Kim Yong Il wrote a short poem along these lines.
金正日写了一首短诗 大致如此
I will quote you the entire poem, just two lines.
我将引用整首诗 只有两行
In the same way that the sunflower can only thrive if it is turned towards the sun,
就像向日葵只有朝向太阳才能茁壮成长
the Korean people can only thrive if their eyes are turned upwards towards their leader, towards himself, of course.
朝鲜人民只有仰望他们的领导人--当然是指他自己--才能茁壮成长
Terror and mercy are thus closely linked.
因此 恐怖与慈悲紧密相连
They are effectively the front and the obverse of the same power structure.
它们实际上是同一权力结构的正面和反面
Only a power which asserts its full terrorist right or capacity to destroy anything and anyone it wants, only such a power can systematically universalize mercy.
只有一个权力 宣称其完全的恐怖权利或能力 能毁灭任何它想毁灭的任何东西和任何人 只有这样的权力才能系统地普及慈悲
Since this power could have destroyed everyone,
因为这种权力本可以摧毁每一个人
Those who survive are all still alive because of the mercy of those in power.
所以幸存的人都是因为掌权者的慈悲才还活着
Consequently, the very fact that we, the subjects of power, are alive is the proof of the power's infinite mercy.
因此 我们作为权力的臣民还活着 这一事实本身就证明了权力的无限仁慈
This is why the more a regime is terrorist, the more its leaders are praised for their infinite love, goodness, and mercy.
这就是为什么一个政权越是恐怖 其领导人就越被赞扬他们的无限爱、善良和慈悲
Theodor Adorno was right to emphasize that in politics, Love is evoked precisely when another democratic legitimization is lacking.
西奥多·阿多诺正确地强调 在政治中 正是在缺乏另一种民主合法化的情况下 爱才被唤起
Loving a leader means you love him for what he is, not for what he does.
爱一个领导意味着你因他是谁而爱他 而不是因为他做了什么
Okay, we may agree with this.
好吧 我们可能同意这一点
So how about the next candidate for love as a political category?
那么 爱情作为政治范畴的下一个可能性又如何呢
The so-called oriental spirituality, Buddhism, with its, or so we are told, more gentle, balanced, holistic, ecological approach.
所谓的东方灵性 佛教 以其我们被告知的更温和、平衡、整体、生态的方法
You know all the stories about how, say, when digging up earth for the foundation of a house, Tibetan Buddhists are careful not to kill any worms and so on.
你知道所有关于 比如 为房子的地基挖土时 藏传佛教徒小心的不杀任何蠕虫等故事
In the whole of the last 150 years,
在过去的150年里
Japan's rapid industrialization and militarization with the ethics of discipline and sacrifice was sustained by the large majority of Zen Buddhist thinkers who today knows that Daisetsutetaro Suzuki himself,
日本的快速工业化和军国主义化 以及纪律和牺牲的伦理 是由大多数禅宗佛教思想家支持的
the high guru of Zen in the United States of the 1960s, supported in his youth in Japan of the 1930s the spirit of utter discipline and militaristic expansion.
比如铃木大拙 1960年代美国的禅宗高僧 在1930年代的日本青年时期 支持了绝对纪律和军国主义扩张的精神
There is no contradiction here, no manipulative perversion of some authentic compassionate insight.
这里没有矛盾 没有对某种真正的慈悲见解的操纵性歪曲
The attitude of total immersion into the selfless now of the instant, the so-called Buddhist enlightenment in which all reflexive distance is lost,
完全沉浸在当下的无我的体验 即所谓的佛教启蒙 其中所有反射性的距离都消失了 （译注：无我中 个体之间的隔阂完全被忽略 所有的小我融合成一个大我）
in short, in which absolute discipline coincides with total spontaneity, perfectly legitimizes our subordination to the militaristic social machine.
简而言之 绝对的纪律与完全的自发性相一致 使我们对军国主义社会机器的服从完全合法化
It's quite interesting to read this, to read Buddhist texts on war, where they claim that openly for ordinary people who don't have time to meditate for years,
读这个非常有趣 读关于战争的佛教文本 他们公开声称对于没有时间进行多年冥想的普通人来说
the best shortcut towards overcoming your false self and reaching nirvana, satori, however we call it, is total subordination to the military discipline.
克服你的虚假自我并达到涅槃、悟道 无论我们如何称呼它 最好的捷径是完全从属于军事纪律
And Suzuki himself wrote a wonderful text where he even gives the advice to the military into how using Buddhism to make killing easier.
铃木大拙自己写了一篇精彩的文本 甚至给军事提供建议 如何利用佛教使杀戮变得更容易
He says, if I persist in my everyday attitude of false belief that I have a self which is the free agent of its acts, then let us say I have to kill one of you.
他说 如果我坚持我日常的虚假信念 认为我有一个自我 可以自由地行动并对行动负责 比方说我不得不杀了你们中的一个
Then this is difficult because you are here, I see it, I look into your eyes, I find it difficult, should I step the knife into you, I feel responsible.
那么这是困难的 因为你在这里 我看到了 我看着你的眼睛 我发现很难 我该不该将刀子插进你 我感到责任
Then Suzuki says, but if you reach Buddhist enlightenment, the thing gets much easier.
然后铃木说 但如果你理解了佛教的启示 事情就容易多了
You no longer believe in your autonomous self,
你不再相信你有一个自主的自我
you perceive yourself as just a void, anonymous, impassive observer of life around you, where phenomena simply are engaged in their cosmic dance, which is a totally neutral process.
你认为自己只是一个虚空 匿名的 冷漠的观察者 观察周围的生活 其中的现象只是参与他们的宇宙之舞 这是一个完全中立的过程
And from this distance, as Suzuki puts it, you simply observe your knife in a cosmic dance of phenomena hitting the eye or the throat of your enemy and so on.
从这个距离来看 正如铃木所说 你只是观察着你的刀子在宇宙现象的舞蹈中击中你敌人的眼睛或喉咙等
Now this is no joking matter because I'm not blaming Buddhism for this.
现在这不是开玩笑的事 因为我不是在责怪佛教
I'm just saying how even the most radical spirituality is no guarantee that we will not be doing horrible things in our daily life.
我只是说 即使是最根本的灵性也不能保证我们在日常生活中不会做可怕的事情
So again, what this means is that the Buddhist all-encompassing compassion has to be opposed to to the Christian, intolerant, violent love.
再说一遍 这意味着佛教包罗万象的慈悲必然与基督教的不宽容、暴力的爱相对立
I want to praise the Christian love.
我想赞美基督教的爱
Although, Christians would probably lynch me for what I will say now.
尽管 基督徒可能会因为我现在要说的而想用私刑来处死我
The Buddhist stance is that of indifference, of quenching all passions, which strive to establish differences.
佛教的立场是冷漠 熄灭一切试图制造差异的激情
While the Christian love is a violent passion to introduce difference, a gap in the order of being, privilege and elevate some object at the expense of others.
而基督教的爱是一种激情 引入差异 在存在的秩序中创造一个间隙 提升并优待某个对象而损害其他对象
Love is violence not in the vulgar sense of the well-known Balkan proverb if he doesn't beat me he doesn't love me.
爱是暴力 并不是在巴尔干俗语“如果他不打我 他就不爱我”所知的粗俗意义上
Violence is already the love choice as such which tears its object out of its context elevating it to the sublime absolute thing.
爱的选择本身就是一种暴力 它将其对象从其上下文中撕裂出来 将其提升为崇高的绝对之物
In In Montenegro folklore, so I was told by Andrei Nikolaidis, my Montenegro friend, the origin of evil is a beautiful woman.
在黑山的民间传说中 据我的黑山朋友安德烈·尼古拉迪斯告诉我 邪恶的起源是一个美丽的女人
She makes men around her lose their balance.
她让她周围的男人失去平衡 （译注：她颠覆了他们的日常生活 使他们无法保持之前的状态）
She literally destabilizes the universe, colors all things with a tone of partiality.
她实际上使宇宙不稳定 用“偏见”给所有事物上色
Among Christian theologists, it was Gilbert Keith Chesterton who fully assumed the consequences of this violent aspect of love.
在基督教神学家中 是吉尔伯特·基思·切斯特顿充分承担了爱的这种暴力方面的后果
One has to get rid of the old platonic topos of love as eros, which gradually elevates itself from love for a particular individual through the love for the beauty of a human body in general
人必须摆脱古老的柏拉图关于爱作为欲望的观念 这种爱从对一个特定个体的爱逐渐提升到对人类身体之美的爱
and then the love of the beautiful form as such to finally the love for the supreme good beyond all forms.
然后是对美本身的爱 最终是对超越所有形式的至高善的爱
True love is precisely the opposite move of forsaking the promise of eternity itself for an imperfect individual
真正的爱恰恰是因为一个不完美的个体 放弃了永恒的承诺 爱是这个相反举动（译注：与柏拉图的爱相反）
What if the gesture of choosing temporal existence, of giving up eternal existence for the sake of love,
如果为了爱而选择短暂存在、放弃了永恒存在 那又怎样呢
From Jesus Christ to, for example, Sigmund in the Act II of Richard Wagner's Die Walkiere,
从耶稣基督到 例如 在理查德·瓦格纳的《女武神》第二幕中的齐格蒙德
who, Sigmund, prefers to stay, to remain a common mortal if his beloved Sieglinde cannot
齐格蒙德 宁愿留下来 成为一个普通的凡人 如果他的爱人希格林德不能跟随他到瓦尔哈拉——死去英雄的永恒居所
What if this is the highest ethical act of them all?
如果这是最高的伦理行为呢
I think this is the message of Christianity which is still alive.
这是基督教的仍然活着的内核
Not forsake all terrestrial things for eternity, but love means I know you are a miserable mortal being, but I'm ready to forsake eternity itself for you.
不是放弃所有尘世之物以求永恒 而是 爱意味着我知道你是一个悲惨的凡人 但我愿意为你放弃永恒本身
Based on this insight, Chesterton rejected the fashionable claim about the alleged spiritual identity of Buddhism and Christianity.
基于这种洞察力 切斯特顿拒绝了关于佛教和基督教所谓精神同一性的流行主张
Here is a well known, I want to repeat it, quote from Chesterton, from his orthodoxy.
这里有一个众所周知的 我想重复它 来自切斯特顿的《正统》的引用
Quote, love desires personality, therefore love desires division.
引用 “爱渴望个性 因此爱渴望分裂 ”
It is the instinct of Christianity to be glad that God has broken the universe into little pieces.
基督教的基础是 欢喜于上帝将宇宙打碎为各个碎片
This is the intellectual abyss between Buddhism and Christianity.
这是佛教与基督教之间的思维的深渊
That, for the Buddhist, personality is the fall of man.
对于佛教徒来说 个性是人的堕落
For the Christian, it is the purpose of God, the whole point of his cosmic idea.
对于基督徒来说 它是上帝的目的 他的宇宙观念的全部要点
The world soul of the theosophists or Buddhists asks man to love it only in order that man may throw himself into it.
神秘主义者或佛教徒的世界灵魂要求人爱它 只是为了让人将自己投入其中
But the divine center of Christianity actually threw man out of it in order that we might love it.
但基督教的神圣核心实际上是将人从中抛出 以便我们能爱它
All modern philosophies are chains which connect and fatter.
所有现代哲学都是连接和束缚的链条
Christianity is a sword which separates and sets free.
基督教是一把分离和释放的剑
No other philosophy makes God actually rejoice in the separation of the universe into different living souls."
没有任何其他哲学能让上帝真正为将宇宙分成不同的活生生的灵魂而感到高兴
A tremendous violence does dwells in the very heart of the Christian notion of love for one's neighbor.
基督教爱邻舍观念的核心中确实存在着巨大的暴力
The violence which finds its most direct expression in a series of Christ's disturbing statements.
这种暴力最直接地表现在基督一系列令人不安的言论中
Here are some of these passages from gospels.
这里是一些来自福音书的摘录
Just listen to them.
只要听听它们
You may be surprised what you find in gospels.
你可能会对你在福音书中这些的内容感到惊讶
Christ saying, talking all the time, do not think that I came to bring peace on the earth.
基督说 一直在说 不要以为我来是为了给地上带来和平
I did not come to bring peace, but a sword.
我来不是为了带来和平 而是带来剑
For I came to set a man against his father, a daughter against her mother, a daughter in law against her mother in law, and men's enemies will be the members of his household.
因为我来是要使人与父亲对立 女儿与母亲对立 媳妇与婆婆对立 人的仇敌将是他自己家里的人
He who loves father or mother more than me is not worthy of me, and he who loves son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me."
谁若爱父母胜过爱我 就不配作我的门徒；谁若爱儿女胜过爱我 就不配作我的门徒 ”
Next quote.
下一个引用
If anyone comes to me and does not hate his own father and mother and wife and children and brothers and sisters, yes, and even his own life, he cannot be my disciple.
如果有人来到我这里 不恨自己的父亲和母亲、妻子和儿女、兄弟姐妹 甚至自己的生命 他就不能成为我的门徒
Next quote, the best one, I think.
下一个引用 我认为是最好的
Perhaps people think that I have come to cast peace upon the world.
也许人们认为我来是为了给世界带来和平
They do not know that I have come to cast conflicts upon the earth.
他们不知道我来是为了在地上引发冲突
Fire, sword, war.
火、剑、战争
For there will be fire in a house.
房中将会起火
There will be three against two and two against three.
将会有三个人对抗两个人 两个人对抗三个人
Father against son, son against father, and they will stand alone, the final quote.
父亲对抗儿子 儿子对抗父亲 他们将孤立无援 最后一个引用
So how are we to read this statement?
那么我们该如何理解这个宣言
And believe me, I know what I'm talking about.
相信我 我知道我在说什么
I'm asking all the time when I engage in debates with Catholic or Protestant or Orthodox priests,
每当我与天主教或新教或东正教的神职人员进行辩论时 我总是在问
I'm asking them, okay, just tell me what this means.
我问他们 好吧 就告诉我这是什么意思
And it's incredible how they try to squeeze out, you know.
他们试图回避的方式令人难以置信
One way is the, how should I call it, the linguistic one.
一种方式是 我该怎么说 语言学的方式
They claim, no, maybe hate is not the right translation.
他们声称 不 也许恨不是正确的翻译
That Christ just wanted to say, if you love some other people more than me, not to hate them.
基督只是想说 如果你爱别人胜过我 不是要恨他们
I claim this is a blasphemy for a true Christian.
我认为对于一个真正的基督徒来说 这是亵渎
God appears here then as a stupid, jealous guy, you know.
上帝在这里显得像一个愚蠢的嫉妒者 你知道的
You can love others, but be sure that you love me more.
你可以爱别人 但确保你更爱我
That's an obscenity.
那是一种亵渎
Or the best answer was given to me by a Polish priest in Warsaw during a debate.
或者最好的答案是在华沙的一次辩论中一个波兰神父给我的
And I asked him, what does this mean?
我问他 这是什么意思
And he told me, oh my god, I didn't expect this question today, I would need more time to prepare the answer.
他告诉我 哦 我的天 我今天没想到会被问到这个问题 我需要更多时间来准备答案
To which I answered him, fuck you, you had 2,000 years to prepare the answer, you know.
对此我回答他 去你的 你有2000年的时间来准备答案 你知道的
I didn't pull out an unknown passage.
我并没有提出一个不为人知的经文
And it's, again, absolutely incredible how they are really not ready to provide a clear answer.
再次 他们真的准备不足以提供一个清晰的答案 这绝对令人难以置信
What do these lines mean?
这些行为意味着什么
To put it in a somewhat simplified way, there are two basic attitudes discernible in the history of religions.
简而言之 宗教历史上可以辨别出两种基本态度
On the one hand, there is the pagan cosmos, the divine hierarchical order of cosmic principles,
一方面 在异教宇宙中 构建了宇宙原则的神圣等级秩序
which, when copied onto society, gives the image of a congruent edifice in which each member is at its own place.
这个秩序被复制到社会上 给出了一个同构的大厦的形象 其中每个成员都有自己的位置 （译注：例如印度婆罗门教的结构）
The supreme good is here, the global balance of principles,
至高无上的善就在这里 所有原则的整体性平衡
and evil stands for their derailment or derangement,
而它们的脱轨或错乱即为邪恶
for the excessive assertion of one principle to the detriment of others,
例如 过度主张某一原则而损害其他原则
of the masculine to the detriment of the feminine, of reason to the detriment of feeling, and so on.
因为男性而损害女性 因为理性而损害感觉 等等
The cosmic balance is then reestablished through the work of justice,
然后通过正义的工作重新建立宇宙平衡 即通过不可抗拒的必然性再次摆正事物 消灭使它们脱轨的元素
With regard to the social body, an individual is good when he or she acts in accordance with his special place within the social edifice,
就社会机体而言 个体在与其在社会建筑中的特殊位置相一致时是善良的
when he respects nature which provides food and shelter, when he shows respect for his superiors,
当他尊重提供食物和庇护的自然时 当他对上级表示尊重时
when he takes care of his followers or children in a fatherly way and so on and so on.
以父亲般的方式照顾他的追随者或孩子 等等等等
And evil is defined as, evil occurs when some particular strata or individuals are no longer satisfied with their proper place.
邪恶被定义为 当一些特定的阶层或个体不再满足于他们适当的位置时 邪恶产生了
Children no longer obey parents, servants no longer obey masters, rulers no longer take care of their subjects and so on and so on.
孩子不再听从父母 仆人不再听从主人 统治者不再照顾他们的臣民 等等等等
I think that this is the ethics which even now is re-emerging often in the guise of some New Age wisdom.
我认为即使是现在 这种伦理也会伪装成某种新时代智慧 重新出现
It's called so-called holistic approach, you know, every element should remain at its proper place, evil is imbalanced and so on and so on.
它被称为所谓的整体论的方法 你知道的 每个元素都应保持在其适当的位置 邪恶是不平衡的 等等等等
I claim that Christianity does precisely the opposite.
我声称基督教做了完全相反的事情
Christianity introduces into the global balanced order a principle totally foreign to it, a The principle that, measured by the standards of a traditional cosmology, cannot but appear as a monstrous distortion.
基督教向整体性平衡秩序中引入了一项与其完全陌生的原则 这一原则以传统宇宙论的标准来衡量 只能表现为一种可怕的扭曲
The principle according to which each individual has an immediate access to the universality.
根据这一原则 每个个体都可以直接进入到普遍性
In Christianity, the universality of the Holy Spirit, or today, the universality of human rights, freedoms, and so on.
在基督教中 圣灵的普遍性 或今天 人权、自由等的普遍性
I can participate in this universal dimension directly, irrespective of my special place within the global social order.
我可以直接参与这个普遍性中 而不管我在这个整体秩序中处于什么位置
So do Christ's scandalous words, which I quoted, not point in the same direction?
那么 我引用的基督的这些令人震惊的话 不也是指向同一个方向吗
Here, of course, we are not dealing with a simple, brutal hatred demanded by a cruel and jealous God.
在这里 当然 我们不是在处理一个简单的、残酷的、由一个残忍和嫉妒的上帝所要求的仇恨
When Christ says if you don't hate your father and mother, you cannot be my follower.
当基督说如果你不恨你的父亲和母亲 你就不能成为我的追随者时
I think the point is not that you should simply hate them as living beings.
我认为重点不是你应该简单地恨他们 即作为生物体存在的他们
I think that in a very simple way you can resolve this dilemma.
我认为你可以以一种非常简单的方式解决这个难题
Father, mother and so on here stand or condense the entire hierarchical social order.
这里的父亲、母亲等代表或凝结了整个等级社会秩序 统治、从属的关系网络 等等
So that the hatred Christ mentions is simply the hatred of established social hierarchy.
因此 基督提到的仇恨仅仅是对既定社会等级的仇恨
You are my follower if, instead of functioning as a part of social hierarchy order,
如果你不是作为社会等级秩序的一部分运作 而是将圣灵和无条件平等的社区视为你真正的家
you see as your true home, as it were, it were Holy Spirit and unconditionally egalitarian community.
你就是我的追随者
Or as St.
或如圣保罗所言
Paul put it, it is love that enjoins us to unplug from our social community into which we were born so that, you know the passage, there are neither men nor women, neither Jews nor Greeks.
是爱驱使我们离开我们出生时所处的的社会团体 你知道那段经文 不再有男人与女人 不再有犹太人与希腊人
This is, I think, the very, I'm simplifying you of course, but nonetheless, the very core of the Christian insight for me.
我认为这是基督教洞察力的核心 当然我在简化 但不管怎样 对我来说是如此
God dies, Christ dies, at the same time the Father dies, all that survives is Holy Spirit,
上帝死了 基督死了 同时父亲也死了 唯一幸存的是圣灵
which is the first name of the Communist Party as we know, and radically egalitarian society which violently opposes social hierarchy, an immediate violent assertion of universal equality.
这是我们所知的Communist Party的名字 也是激进平等主义社会的名字 它暴力反对社会等级制度 是对普遍平等的直接暴力主张
And it is against this Christian background that we should read Che Guevara's well-known statement on revolutionary love, a quote from Che Guevara.
正是在这样的基督教背景下 我们应该读一下切·格瓦拉那句著名的革命爱情宣言 这是切·格瓦拉的名言
At the risk of seeming ridiculous, let me say that the true revolutionary is guided by great feelings of love.
冒着显得荒谬的风险 让我说 真正的革命者是受伟大的爱的情感引导的
It is impossible to think of a genuine revolutionary lacking this quality, end of quote.
难以想象一个缺乏这种品质的真正的革命者 引用结束 （译注：我失骄杨君失柳 杨柳轻飏直上重霄九）
There is a further step to be made here.
更近一步 格瓦拉关于真正的革命者是由伟大的爱的感觉引导的说法 应该与他关于革命者是杀人机器的这个更有问题的说法一起阅读
Now comes the other statement.
现在来看另一个声明
Hatred is an element of struggle, relentless hatred of the enemy that impels us over and beyond the natural limitations of men and transforms us into effective, violent, selective, and cold killing machines.
仇恨是斗争的元素 对敌人的无情仇恨使我们超越人的自然限制 并将我们转变为有效的、暴力的、选择性的、冷酷的杀戮机器
That's the other quote.
那是另一个引用
These two, apparently opposite stances, are united in Che Guevara's well-known motto.
这两个看似相反的立场 在切·格瓦拉的著名座右铭中统一起来
One must endure, become hard, toughen oneself, without losing tenderness, end of quote.
一个人必须忍耐 变得坚强 坚强自己 但又不失温柔 引用结束
I think Guevara is here basically paraphrasing Christ's declaration of the unity of love and sword.
我认为格瓦拉在这里基本上是在复述基督关于爱和剑统一的宣言
In both cases, the underlying paradox is that what makes love angelic, what elevates it over mere unstable, pathetic sentimentality is its cruelty itself, its link with violence.
在这两种情况下 潜在的悖论在于 使爱变得天使般的东西 使爱超越单纯不稳定、可悲的多愁善感的东西 是它本身的残酷性 是它与暴力的联系
So while Guevara certainly believed in the transformative power of love, he would never have been caught humming all you need is love.
所以 虽然格瓦拉肯定相信爱的变革力量 但他绝不会哼唱“你所需要的就是爱”
What you need is to love with hatred, or another strange bad fellow here.
你需要的是带着仇恨去爱 或者另外的可能是
As Seren Kierkegaard put it long ago, the necessary consequence, the truth, of the Christian demand to love one's enemy is,
正如克尔凯郭尔很久以前所说 基督教要求爱敌人的必然后果
quote from Kierkegaard, is the demand to hate the beloved out of love and in love.
克尔凯郭尔的引用 这是一个要求 出于爱 而去恨你所爱之人
So high, humanly speaking, to a kind of madness, can Christianity press the demand of love, is love is to be the fulfillment of the law.
从人的角度来说 基督教对爱的要求如此之高 达到了一种疯狂的地步 爱就是要成全律法
Therefore, it teaches that the Christian shall, if it is demanded, be capable of hating his father and mother and sister and beloved, end of quote.
因此 它教导说基督徒若被要求 必须能够恨他的父亲母亲姐妹和所爱的人 引号结束
With regard to social order, this means that the authentic Christian tradition rejects the wisdom that the hierarchical order is our faith,
关于社会秩序 这意味着真正的基督教传统拒绝了层级秩序即是我们信仰的智慧
that all attempts to mess with it and to create another egalitarian order have to end up in destructive horror.
所有试图搅乱它并创造另一种平等秩序的尝试都必将以破坏性的恐怖结束
Agape is political love, and following Terry Eagleton, this is how I would propose to translate agape, is simply political love.
神之爱是政治爱 按照泰瑞·伊格尔顿的说法 我提议将神之爱翻译为简单的政治爱
Agape means that the unconditional egalitarian love for the neighbor can serve as the foundation for a new social order.
神之爱意味着对邻居的无条件平等爱可以作为新社会秩序的基础
The form of appearance of this love is the so-called apocalyptic millenarism or the idea of communism,
这种爱的表现形式是所谓的末世千年主义或communism理念 （译注：末日千年主义是一种宗教信仰和思想 它预言将会有一段被称为“千年王国”的时期 在这一时期 世界将会经历彻底的道德和精神上的转变 正义将会统治地球 通常伴随着神或救世主的回归）
the urge to realize an egalitarian social order of solidarity.
实现一个平等的团结社会秩序的冲动
Love is the force of this universal link which in an emancipatory collective connects people directly in their singularity, bypassing their particular hierarchic determinations.
爱是这种普遍联系的力量 在一个解放的集体中 爱将人们的独特性直接联系起来 绕过了他们特定的等级制度
Terror is terror out of love for the universal singular others against the particular.
恐怖是出于对普遍的、独特的、特殊的他人的爱而产生的恐怖
This terror names exactly the same as the work of love.
这种恐怖的名字与爱情的作品如出一辙
So my approach to the fundamental is terrorists,
因此 我对恐怖分子的基本态度是
Islamist or Christian, should be that precisely they are not terrorists in the right way,
无论是伊斯兰主义者还是基督教徒 准确地说 他们不是恐怖分子
that they shirk from authentic terror of the work of love.
他们逃避对爱的真正恐惧
Now you will be saying, am I crazy?
现在你们会说 我疯了吗
What distinguishes this from a murderous terrorist who kills but claiming I'm killing you because of your eternal soul and so on and so on?
这与一个谋杀性恐怖分子有何区别 他杀人却声称我是因为你的永恒灵魂等等而杀你
I will try to explain this in the remaining part by beginning with what is precisely the form of non-love today which poses as love, charity.
我将尝试在剩余的部分解释这一点 首先是今天哪种形式的非爱伪装成爱 慈善
one again of the names and practices of non-love today.
再一次 慈善是今天非爱的名字和做法之一
When we see an ad with starving children in Africa with a call to do something to help them,
当我们看到一则有关非洲饥饿儿童的广告 呼吁做些什么来帮助他们时
like something like for the price of a couple of cappuccinos you can save their life and so on,
比如说以几杯卡布奇诺的价格你可以拯救他们的生命之类的
I claim that the true message is something like don't think, don't politicize, forget about the true causes of their poverty.
我声称真正的信息是类似于不要思考 不要政治化 忘记他们贫困的真正原因
Just act, contribute money, so that you will not have to think.
只是行动 贡献金钱 这样你就不必思考
In short, the true message is, for the price of a couple of cappuccinos,
简而言之 真正的信息是 以几杯卡布奇诺的价格
you can continue your ignorant, pleasurable life, not only not feeling any guilt, but even feeling good for participating in the struggle against suffering.
你可以继续你的无知、愉悦的生活 不仅不感到任何罪恶感 甚至因参与抗击苦难而感到良好
So how would this notion of love, which is the opposite of charity, charity is false love,
那么 与慈善相反的爱的概念 慈善是虚假的爱
because charity is love with the true aim of which is to make you feel good.
因为慈善是真正目的是让你感觉良好的爱
My God, what a great man I am, you see.
我的天啊 看看我多伟大
I'm helping all the children starving in Somalia and so on and so on.
我正在帮助索马里所有饥饿的儿童等等
How would the authentic, violent love help us to orient ourselves today?
真正的、暴力的爱如何帮助我们今天定位自己
Let me begin with a wonderful quote from last Christmas issue of the magazine Spectator.
让我从《旁观者》杂志去年圣诞节特刊的一段精彩引语开始
In this issue, there is an editorial entitled why 2012 was the best year ever.
在这期杂志中 有一篇题为《为什么2012年是有史以来最好的一年》的社论
This editorial argues against the perception that we live in a dangerous, cruel world where things are bad and getting worse.
这篇社论反驳了我们生活在一个危险、残酷的世界中 事情糟糕并且越来越糟的看法
Here is the first paragraph of this editorial.
以下是这篇社论的第一段
I quote, it may not feel like it, but 2012 has been the greatest year in the history of the world.
我引用 “可能感觉不像 但2012年已经成为世界历史上最伟大的一年
That sounds like an extravagant claim, it is borne out by evidence.
这听起来像是一个夸张的说法 但它是有证据支持的
Never has there been less hunger, less disease, or more prosperity.
从未有过如此少的饥饿、疾病或更多的繁荣
The West remains in the economic doldrums, but most developing countries are charging ahead and people are being lifted out of poverty at the fastest rate ever recorded.
西方仍处于经济低迷 但大多数发展东印度家正飞速前进 人们被以前所未有的最快速度脱离贫困
The death toll inflicted by war and natural disasters is also mercifully low.
战争和自然灾害造成的死亡人数也是令人宽慰的低
We are living in a golden age."
我们正生活在一个黄金时代 ”
End of quote.
引用结束
Now the first thing to add here, even if I, why not, I always like to concede to the devil what belongs to the devil,
现在要补充的第一件事 即使我 为什么不 我总是喜欢承认恶魔的东西归恶魔
even many things are true in this statement, but the first thing to add is that people rebel not when things are really bad, but when their expectations are disappointed.
即使这个声明中的许多东西是真的 但要补充的第一件事是人们反叛不是因为情况真的很糟 而是因为他们的期望受到了失望
French Revolution took place after the king and the nobles were for decades gradually losing their full hold on power.
法国大革命发生在国王和贵族几十年来逐渐失去他们的全部控制权之后
The 1956 anti-communist revolt in Hungary exploded after Imre Nagy, the reformist prime minister later shot by the Soviets,
1956年匈牙利的反communism起义在伊姆雷·纳吉（后来被苏联枪杀的改革派总理）已经担任总理两年之后 以及允许知识分子之间相对自由的辩论之后爆发
was already prime minister for two years and after relatively free debates among intellectuals were allowed.
纳吉已经是总理两年了 此后允许知识分子之间相对自由的辩论
Even
甚至
A closer example, people rebelled in Egypt in 2011 because there was some minimal economic progress under Mubarak, giving rise to a whole class of educated young people who participated in the universal digital culture.
更近的一个例子 人们在2011年在埃及反叛 因为在穆巴拉克统治下有一些最小的经济进步 催生了一整个受过教育的年轻人阶层 他们参与了全球数字文化
And this is why the Chinese communists are right to be in panic, precisely because on average Chinese are now living considerably better than 40 years ago.
这就是为什么东印度Communist Party有理由恐慌 因为平均而言 东印度现在的生活比40年前好得多
But the social antagonisms between the newly reached and the rest exploded, plus expectations are much higher.
但是新富裕者和其他人之间的社会对立爆炸了 加上期望值更高了
That's the problem with development and progress.
这就是发展和进步的问题
They are always uneven, they give birth to new instabilities and antagonisms, they generate new expectations which cannot be met.
它们总是不均衡的 它们孕育出新的不稳定和对立 产生了无法满足的新期望
In Tunisia or Egypt, just prior to the Arab Spring, the majority probably lived a little bit better than decades ago, but the standard by which they measured their satisfaction was much higher.
在突尼斯或埃及 就在阿拉伯之春爆发之前 大多数人可能比几十年前生活得稍好一些 但他们衡量满意度的标准却高得多
So yes, the spectator is in principle right, claiming that we live in a golden era, but the very facts that the spectator emphasizes are creating conditions for revolt and rebellion.
所以是的 社论原则上是对的 声称我们生活在一个黄金时代 但社论强调的事实正创造了叛乱和反叛的条件
So again, what rebellion.
那么再次 是哪种叛乱
There is a more down-to-earth version of this claim of Spectator, which I often hear in mass media, especially when I visit non-European countries.
它的这种说法有一个更实际的版本 我经常在大众媒体上听到这种说法 尤其是当我访问非欧洲国家时
They laugh at me and they say, crisis, what crisis are you talking about?
他们嘲笑我 说 危机 你在说什么危机
Look at the BRIC countries, Poland, South Korea, Singapore, Peru, even many sub-Saharan African states.
看看金砖国家、波兰、韩国、新加坡、秘鲁 甚至许多撒哈拉以南非洲国家
They are all progressing.
他们都在进步
The losers are only West Europe and up to a point the United States.
只有西欧和在某种程度上的美国是输家
So we are not dealing with a global crisis, but just with the shift of the dynamics of progress away from the West.
所以我们面对的不是全球性危机 而只是进步动力从西方转移的情况
It's important symbol of this shift, not the fact that recently many people from Portugal, a country in deep crisis, are returning to Mozambique and Angola, ex-colonies of Portugal, but this time as economic immigrants not as colonizers.
这种转移的一个重要象征不是葡萄牙人最近从深度危机的国家葡萄牙返回莫桑比克和安哥拉这些前殖民地 而这次是作为经济移民而不是殖民者
So what if our much-decried crisis is a mere local crisis in an overall progress?
那么 如果我们所诟病的危机仅仅是在整体进步中的局部危机呢
Even with regard to human rights, is the situation in China and Russia now not much better than 50 years ago?
即使对人权来说 东印度和俄罗斯现在的状况难道不比50年前好得多吗
Decrying the ongoing crisis as a global phenomenon is thus a typical Eurocentrist view and the view coming from leftists who are usually pride, who usually pride themselves on their anti Eurocentrism.
因此 谴责当前的危机是一种全球现象是一种典型的欧洲中心主义观点 这种观点来自通常骄傲的左派 他们通常为自己的反欧洲中心主义而自豪
There is a partial truth in it and again admit what is true.
其中有部分事实 再次承认事实
It's true that globally economy is progressing.
全球经济确实在进步 这是真的
I mean the crisis in some sense is not global but nonetheless I think we should restrain here our anti-colonialist joy a little bit.
我的意思是 从某种意义上说 危机并不是全球性的 但尽管如此 我认为我们应该在这里对我们的反殖民主义喜悦稍加克制
The question to be raised is if Europe is in gradual decay what is replacing its hegemon?
要提出的问题是 如果欧洲正在逐渐衰退 什么在取代它的霸权
Capitalism with Asian values which of course has nothing to do with Asian people and everything with the clear and present tendency of contemporary capitalism as such everywhere to suspend or at least limit constrained democracy.
那就是带有亚洲价值的资本主义 当然 这与亚洲人民无关 与当代资本主义的明显且普遍趋势——暂停或至少限制约束民主——有关
From Marx on the The truly radical left was never simply progressist, it was always obsessed by the question, what is the hidden price of progress?
从马克思开始 真正的激进左派从来不仅仅是进步主义者 它总是被一个问题所困扰 进步的隐藏代价是什么
Marx was fascinated by capitalism, by the unheard-of productivity it unleashed.
马克思被资本主义的前所未有的生产力所吸引
He just insisted that this very success engenders antagonisms.
他只是坚持认为这种成功产生了对立
And we should do the same with today's progress of global capitalism, keep in view its dark underside.
我们应该对当今全球资本主义的进步也做同样的事情 关注它的阴暗面
How?
如何
Where?
在哪里
First I want to note something about the status of universality because critics of universality,
首先我想说一些关于普遍性地位的事情 因为批评普遍性的人
sorry, critics of Eurocentrism usually emphasize the ideological limitation, lie, deception of Western European universalism, claiming that for example, and they are right up to a point,
抱歉 通常批评欧洲中心主义的人会强调普遍性的意识形态限制、谎言、欺骗 声称例如 他们在某种程度上是对的
when we talk about human rights we privilege a certain ideological set of human rights specific of Western individualist societies and so on and so on.
当我们谈论人权时 我们偏爱某种特定于西方个人主义社会的人权意识形态集合等等
That's true, but the situation is a little bit more complicated, because in a properly dialectical Marxist perspective, yes, every universality can be false.
这是真的 但情况稍微复杂一些 因为在一个恰当的辩证的马克思主义视角中 是的 每一个普遍性都可以是虚假的
It is always over-determined by some particular content.
它总是被某些特定内容过度决定
For example, human rights, yes, but if you look closely at it, human rights secretly privilege white male people of some property and so on and so on.
例如 人权 是的 但如果你仔细看 人权秘密地偏爱一些有财产的白人男性等等
So whenever we, it's clear that this is in some sense true.
所以每当我们 很明显这在某种意义上是真的
For example, when we talk about Chinese philosophy, it's clear that we are doing a Eurocentrist operation
例如 当我们谈论东印度哲学时 很明显我们正在做一个欧洲中心主义的操作
because philosophy, as we know it, emerged in Europe and if we apply the same notion to Chinese thought, that Chinese thought is automatically in a disadvantage, and so on and so on.
因为我们所知的哲学是在欧洲出现的 如果我们将同样的概念应用于东印度思想 那么东印度思想自动处于劣势 等等
But this historicist relativism, beware how universality can be a false universality, is just one side of the story.
但是这种历史相对主义 要警惕普遍性如何可能是假的普遍性 只是故事的一面
Marx is saying something, I think, which is much more actual today, that we are not only less universal than we think.
马克思在说的某事 我认为今天更加实际 那就是我们不仅比我们认为的更不普遍
We think universal human rights, we privilege European, patriarchal, whatever rights.
我们认为的普遍人权 我们偏爱欧洲的、父权的等等权利
We are also much more universal, much more universal than we think we are.
我们也比我们认为的要更普遍 更普遍
For Marx the uniqueness of capitalism is that as agents on a market, we ourselves as individuals occupies a universal position
对于马克思而言 资本主义的独特之处在于作为市场上的代理人 我们自己作为个体占据了一个普遍的位置
in the sense that we relate to ourselves as universal subjects, universal in the sense that we are no longer fully rooted in or identified with a particular social, ideological, and so on positions.
意味着我们将自己视为普遍主体 普遍到我们不再完全根植于或认同于特定的社会、意识形态等位置
It's not a universality with regard to others.
这不是与他人相关的普遍性
I relate to myself as someone who, for example, today I'm an engineer, I lose this work tomorrow, I can be a taxi driver, then I don't know what.
我将自己视为一个人 例如 今天我是一个工程师 明天我失去这份工作 我可以成为一个出租车司机 然后我不知道会是什么
Our particular field of work is experienced as something ultimately contingent.
我们特定的工作领域被体验为某种最终是偶然的
The same goes for market commodities and so on.
市场商品等等也是如此
So universality is a way of life, as it were.
所以普遍性是一种生活方式 可以这么说
It's a mode of our immediate experience.
这是我们直接经验的一种模式
And now the big question is what role with regard to the process of emancipation this brutal late capitalist universality,
现在最大的问题是 这种残酷的晚期资本主义普遍性在解放过程中扮演什么角色
this unheard of force of capitalism to dissolve our particular modes of life and so on has.
资本主义以前所未有的力量溶解了我们特定的生活方式
I want now to do something extremely problematic.
我现在要做一件极其有问题的事情
I want to rehabilitate a text of Marx, rather two texts which are usually dismissed by post-colonial studies as embarrassing cases of Marxist racism and Eurocentrism.
我想要为马克思的一段文字 准确地说是两段文字进行辩护 这些文字通常被后殖民研究视为马克思主义种族主义和欧洲中心主义的尴尬案例而被忽视
He's too short from 1,853 articles on India.
他在1853年关于印度的文章中提到了这些
The British rule in India and the future results of British rule in India.
《英国在印度的统治》和《英国在印度统治的未来结果》
Marx admits here without restraint the brutality and exploitative hypocrisy of the British colonization of India,
马克思在这里毫无保留地承认了英国对印度的殖民的残酷性和剥削性虚伪
which goes up to the systematic use of torture prohibited in the West, but outsourced to India.
这直到西方被禁止的系统性使用酷刑 但却外包到了印度
Really, nothing new under the sun.
真的 太阳底下没有新鲜事
There were Guantanamo's already in the midst of the 19th century British empire.
19世纪中叶的英帝国中已经存在着像关塔那摩这样的地方 （译注：关塔那摩湾拘留营 位于古巴 这个拘留营是在2002年 即911恐怖袭击之后不久 由美国政府设立的 旨在关押和审讯涉嫌恐怖主义的囚犯）
The quote from Marx, the profound hypocrisy and inherent barbarism of bourgeois civilization lies unveiled before our eyes, turning from its home,
马克思引述：“资产阶级文明的深刻虚伪和固有野蛮在我们眼前被揭露 从其本土转向殖民地 在本土它好像尊重表面形式 在殖民地则赤裸裸 ”
End of quote.
引述结束
All that Marx adds is, quote, England has broken down the entire framework of Indian society without any symptoms of reconstitution yet appearing.
马克思补充道：“英国打破了印度社会的整个框架 而新的构建迹象尚未出现
This loss of its old world, with no gain of a new one, imparts a particular kind of melancholy to the present misery of the Hindu and separates Hindustan, ruled by Britain,
这种失去旧世界而未获得新世界的情况 给当下印度人的悲哀带来了特殊的忧郁 使得英国统治下的印度斯坦
from all its ancient traditions and from the whole of its past history.
与其所有古老的传统和整个过去的历史隔绝
England, it is true, is causing a social revolution in Hindustan, a revolution which was actuated only by the vilest interests and was stupid in her manner of enforcing this interest.
确实 英国在印度斯坦引发了一场社会革命 这场革命只是由最卑鄙的利益驱动 并且在强制这种利益的方式上愚蠢至极
But that is not the question.
但这不是问题所在
The question is, can mankind fulfill its destiny without a fundamental revolution in the social state of Asia?
问题是 人类能否在不对亚洲的社会状态进行根本性革命的情况下完成其命运
If not, whatever may have been the crime of England,
如果不能 无论英国犯下了何种罪行
she was, England was the unconscious tool of history in bringing about the revolution.
她 英国 是历史的无意识工具 在促成这场革命
Now this is the Marx usually attacked.
现在这就是通常被攻击的马克思
One should not dismiss here the talk of the unconscious tool of history.
在这里 不应该忽视“历史的无意识工具”的讨论
Marx is not a naive teleologist, claiming oh, the British brutal exploitation of India was a tool of some higher historical reason
马克思不是一个幼稚的目的论者 声称哦 英国对印度的残酷剥削是某种更高历史理由的工具
which made it an instrument of future progress and so on and so on.
这使它成为未来进步的工具等等
All Marx claims is that the British colonization of India
马克思所声称的全部是 英国对印度的殖民
unintendedly created conditions for the double liberation of India from the constraints of its own traditions as well as from colonization itself.
无意中创造了条件 使印度既能从其自身传统的束缚中解放出来 也能从殖民本身中解放出来
And there is not an empirical proof of this.
而这并非没有实证证据
Do you know that the British tried to,
你知道吗 英国人试图
They were intelligent enough, the British colonizers,
他们足够聪明 英国的殖民者
they knew that if they allow their colonization to simply dissolve traditional ideological, social, Indian edifice, castes, and so on, that this may create revolutionary upheavals in India.
他们知道 如果他们允许他们的殖民活动简单地瓦解印度的传统意识形态、社会结构、种姓等 这可能会在印度创造革命性的动荡
So it's interesting to notice how, from the very beginning of their colonialist critics' claim, British colonizers wanted us to lose our tradition and to impose Western standards.
因此 有趣的是 殖民主义批评者的主张 英国殖民者一开始就希望我们失去传统并强加西方标准
No, on the contrary.
不 恰恰相反
They put hard work into re-establishing some kind of resuscitating old, stable, value, ideological, religious systems, which would keep India a stable, inert society, ready to be exploited.
他们努力重新建立某种复兴旧的、稳定的、价值观、意识形态、宗教体系 这将使印度保持一个稳定、惰性的社会 准备好被剥削
For example, the ultimate Indian ideological textbook,
例如 最终的印度意识形态教科书
The Loss of Manu, a pretty terrifying book,
《摩奴法典》 一本相当恐怖的书
a detailed justification of caste system with detailed descriptions what were to do.
详细地为种姓制度辩护 描述了应当做什么
You know, I learned with surprise for my Indian friends that in 17th century at least this book was half forgotten.
你知道 我惊讶地从我的印度朋友那里得知 至少在17世纪 这本书已经被半遗忘
It was just lost in different transcriptions.
它只是在不同的抄本中丢失
It is in the earlier 19th century that the British colonizers reestablished, resuscitated this book.
是在19世纪早期 英国殖民者重新确立、复兴了这本书
So I claim in this sense that all this topic about respect for local cultures and so on was from the very beginning the crucial part of the process of colonization.
因此 我认为在这个意义上 所有这些关于尊重当地文化等话题 从一开始就是殖民过程的关键部分
British didn't want for the Indians to become like them.
英国人不希望印度人变得像他们
They want them in their inner traditional ways and they even went as far as to praise immensely the superiority of their spirituality.
他们希望他们保留自己的传统方式 甚至极力赞扬他们的精神优越性
The standard memoir of British colonizers in India reached something like that.
英国殖民者在印度的标准回忆录是这样说的
Yes, we may be richer materially, the British.
是的 我们或许在物质上更富有 英国人
Yes, we bring progress and industry to India.
是的 我们给印度带来了进步和工业
But when you see a simple yogi saint praising there, don't you feel how worthless we are?
但当你看到一个纯净的瑜伽圣人在那里赞美时 你不觉得我们是多么无价值吗
Don't you feel the infinite depth of that simple spirituality and so on and so on.
你不觉得那种简单的精神深度是无限的吗 等等
I claim that this is absolutely crucial.
我认为这是绝对关键的
You take this false respect for the other from colonialism.
你从殖民主义中拿走这种对他者的虚假尊重
You lose colonialism itself.
你就失去了殖民主义本身
What do we have to accept here?
我们需要接受什么呢
We have to accept that.
我们需要接受那个
A quote from another great delectician, Richard Wagner, from his Parsifal,
引用另一个伟大的辩证家理查德·瓦格纳在他的《帕西法尔》中的话
Die wunder schlicht der spärnur der sich luch.
“伤口只能由那把造成它的长矛治愈 ”
The wound can only be healed by the very spear that smote it.
伤口只能由那把造成它的长矛治愈
That is to say, we should insist on what Marx insists.
也就是说 我们应该坚持马克思所坚持的
On this radical, brutal, but radical ambiguity of colonization.
关于殖民的这种激进、残酷但根本的模糊性
That is to say that it is the very power of social disintegration brought by, unleashed by colonization, all traditional forms of identity, traditional ethical morphs dissolve and so on, which at the same time opens up the space for liberation, also for anti-colonial liberation.
也就是说 正是殖民带来、释放的社会解体的力量 所有传统的身份形式、传统的伦理形态都在溶解等等 这同时为解放开辟了空间 也为反殖民解放开辟了空间
What do we mean by this?
我们这样说是什么意思
Let me give you another example from India itself.
让我给你们再举一个来自印度本身的例子
When I was there two years ago, I got into a heated debate with some Indian cultural theorists who complained about the fact that they had to use English language as their expression.
两年前我在那里的时候 我与一些印度文化理论家进行了激烈的辩论 他们抱怨不得不使用英语作为他们的表达方式
They claimed this is already a form of cultural colonization which censors our true identity.
他们声称这已经是一种文化殖民的形式 审查了我们的真实身份
They claim, can you see how strong colonization is?
他们说 你能看到殖民有多强大吗
Even now, when we try to formulate our project of liberation from colonialism, we have to do it in the language of the colonizers.
即使现在 当我们尝试构建我们的从殖民主义解放出来的项目时 我们不得不用殖民者的语言来做
This was a quote from one of them.
这是其中一个人的引言
We have to speak in an imposed foreign language to express our innermost identity.
我们必须用一种强加的外语来表达我们最深刻的身份
And that does not put us in a position of radical alienation.
这难道不让我们处于一种根本性的异化位置吗
Even our resistance to colonization has to be formulated in the language of the colonizer.
即使我们对殖民的抵抗也必须用殖民者的语言来表达
My answer to this was yes, but this imposition of English,
我的回答是 是的 但英语这种外来语言的强加
a foreign language, created the very x unknown quantity which is oppressed by it.
创造了正是被它压迫的未知量
That is to say, and this was my message, and it's typical what happened to me.
也就是说 这是我的信息 而且典型的是我遇到的情况
I was shocked how this message was received differently among my partners in debate there, but in strict correlation to the social status.
我震惊地发现这个信息在我的辩论伙伴中被不同地接收 但与社会地位严格相关
The top Brahmin intellectuals shouted at me as colonizer blah blah.
顶级婆罗门知识分子对我大喊殖民者之类的话
The Dalits, the untouchables immediately accepted it.
而达利特——不可接触者——立即接受了它
Namely, my message was, it's true, when you are forced to speak a foreign language,
也就是说 我的信息是 确实 当你被迫说一种外语时
you feel deprived of the very core of your identity.
你会感到被剥夺了你身份的核心
But my thesis is here a much more radical one.
但我的论点在这里更加激进
It is that that which you feel deprived of is a specter engendered by this very colonial imposition of a foreign language.
你感到被剥夺的那个东西 正是这种殖民的强加外语所产生的幽灵
In other words, it's a very refined dialectical paradox.
换句话说 这是一个非常精细的辩证悖论
If some of you are philosophers, Hegel uses a wonderful term, the absoluter Gegenstoß, the absolute recoil counterpounce for this.
如果你们中有哲学家 黑格尔使用了一个绝妙的术语 “绝对的反击”来形容这个
The very loss in appropriately dialectical notion of history, the very loss of something creates the lost dimension.
在适当的辩证历史观中 某物的丧失恰恰创造了丢失的维度
We don't have a pre-colonial India and then brutal colonization which makes the people aware what they lost and then in anti-colonial struggle they are trying to regain what they lost.
我们没有这个过程 即一个前殖民的印度 然后是残酷的殖民化 使人们意识到他们失去了什么 然后在反殖民斗争中他们试图重新获得失去的东西
No, the pre-colonial India was something totally different.
不 前殖民的印度完全是另一回事
It's irredeemably lost.
它无可挽回地丢失了
In so far as it's not lost, it precisely serves colonizers.
它没有丢失的部分正准确地服务于殖民者
This new dimension that you are craving for, for example, in the case of India, a new modern democratic India,
你渴望的这个新维度 例如在印度的情况下 一个新的现代民主印度
the very program of decolonization is something engendered by colonization itself as a reaction to it.
非殖民化计划本身就是殖民化本身作为对殖民化的反应而产生的
Another example to make this clear, you know he's one of my heroes, Malcolm X, the great American, a little bit more violent than Martin Luther King, fighter for black rights.
再举一个例子来说明这一点 你们知道我的英雄之一 马尔科姆·X 伟大的美国黑人权利斗士 比马丁·路德·金更有些暴力
You know why he has chosen this no family name, but just X, X unknown quantity instead of,
你们知道他为什么选择了X这个无家族姓氏 而不是
I don't know what family name.
我不知道什么家族姓氏
Of course, at an immediate level, he wanted to emphasize how the blacks, by being torn out of their African ancestral homes, that they are deprived of their roots.
当然 在直接层面上 他想强调黑人被从他们非洲的祖先家园中撕裂出来 他们被剥夺了他们的根
But the program of Malcolm X was not, so let's return to those roots.
但马尔科姆·X的计划不是 让我们返回那些根源
But X means, what if we grasp this very void into which our enslavement put us?
X意味着 如果我们抓住这个奴役是我们产生出的虚空本身 会怎样
the fact that we don't have any genuine tradition to rely on, that we have to, as it were, collectively reinvent our identity as a unique opportunity of freedom.
事实上 我们没有任何真正的传统可以依赖 我们必须集体重塑我们的身份 将其作为获得自由的独特机会
And it's also clear that he followed this line.
他成为了穆斯林
The one who was preaching return to African roots was King Butelezi, a local king there, who as we all know was collaborating with apartheid forces.
宣扬回归非洲根源的是布特莱齐国王 那里的一个地方国王 我们都知道他与种族隔离势力合作
He was even directly financed by the Pretoria apartheid government.
他甚至直接得到了比勒陀利亚种族隔离政府的资助
No, to see the truth of what I'm saying, you should really read history.
不 要看到我所说的真相 你真的应该读历史
For example, you should read the apartheid, white racist justification of, well, apartheid system.
例如 你应该阅读种族隔离制度、白人种族主义者对种族隔离制度的辩护
It was not we whites are more.
这不是我们白人更优越
Of course, it was this de facto, but the justification was something like what a precious difference of cultures we have here.
当然 事实上是这样 但辩护是类似于我们这里有多么珍贵的文化差异
We have Bushmen, Hottentot, this, that.
我们有布什曼人、霍顿人 这个 那个
If we allow them, if we give them equality in the modern sense, all this pressure, spiritual traditions, all we get lost in our vulgar westerns, mechanical, imperialist, non-holistic, whatever civilization.
如果我们允许他们 如果我们以现代意义上给予他们平等 那么所有这些珍贵的精神传统 都会在我们粗俗的西方、机械的、帝国主义的、非整体性的等等文明中丢失
The idea was strictly, of course, a fake multiculturalism, but nonetheless a multiculturalism.
这个想法严格来说当然是假的多元文化主义 但无论如何是一种多元文化主义
And again, the greatness of Mandela and so on was always to insist.
再次强调 曼德拉等人的伟大之处一直在于坚持
No, we should beat the white people at their own feet by being more universal than they are.
不 我们应该在他们的领域里打败白人 通过比他们更普世
And so again, back to, sorry, where are we?
所以 再次回到 对不起 我们在哪里
Yes, back to India, I think that the solution is not to look for some lost British identity, but it's a crazy paradoxical solution, but accepted by Dalits and so on,
是的 回到印度 我认为解决方案不是寻找一些失去的英国身份 但这是一个疯狂的自相矛盾的解决方案 但被达利特人等接受
to see decolonization as a welcome chance of getting rid of old rules,
即 将非殖民化视为摆脱旧规则的一个受欢迎的机会 并将印度现在被剥夺他们适当传统的事实 再次视为实现一个更加开放、平等、民主社会的机会
And believe me or not, Western conservatives are becoming aware of it.
信不信由你 西方保守派开始意识到这一点
For example, I read a wonderful complaint by an American conservative linguist who says
例如 我读到一个美国保守派语言学家的精彩抱怨 他说
we shouldn't be too glad about the primacy of English language because he says, and he was right, that the language, the English language which is now becoming lingua franca
我们不应该对英语的主导地位太过高兴 因为他说 他是对的 现在成为通用语的英语
is no longer the old English of true British people, but it is an English spoken by Indian merchants in Mumbai by Singapore bankers and so on and so on.
不再是真正英国人的旧英语 而是由孟买的印度商人、新加坡银行家等等说的英语
The English itself as universal language is being stolen from British people themselves.
英语本身作为通用语言 正从英国人自己那里被窃取
So again, this is what I see as the core of Marxist insight.
所以 这正是我看到的马克思洞察的核心
I don't believe in anti-colonial resistance on behalf of any return to some primordial lost roots and so on and so on.
我不相信任何基于回归某种原始失落根源的反殖民抵抗等等
If anything, we should advocate a never further universalization, further loss of our local or whatever roots.
如果有什么 我们应该主张进一步的普遍化 进一步失去我们的本地或任何根源
Next point, and now I am approaching the end, I want to make very briefly is that what does this mean again for us concretely today?
下一点 现在我接近结束了 我想非常简短地说明的是 这对我们今天具体意味着什么
There is a certain, how should I call it, paradigm which unites many modern, or not so modern, philosophers.
有一种范式 将许多现代或不那么现代的哲学家联合起来
Let's call it Helderlin paradigm, by Helderlin I mean Friedrich Helderlin, the great German poet whose best known headline, as you know, is Wodas gefär ist wechs das retende Auch,
让我们称之为赫尔德林范式 赫尔德林我指的是弗里德里希·赫尔德林 伟大的德国诗人 他最著名的一句话 正如你们所知 是“危险增长的地方 拯救我们的东西也随之增长”
The idea is that our epoch is the epoch of extreme danger, extreme alienation for Marx
意思是 我们的时代是极端危险、极端异化的时代 对马克思来说
or loss of our roots in global technology for Heidegger, but at this point of extreme loss is also the opportunity for what Heidegger calls the care for the reversal.
或对海德格来说是在全球技术中失去我们的根源 但在这个极端丧失的点上也是海德格所说的关怀转向的机会
When things are lost, there is a chance of reversal.
当事物丧失时 就有了逆转的机会
For example, the whole eschatology of Marx is based on this.
例如 马克思的整个末世论就是基于这一点 资本主义是彻底的异化 工人完全被剥夺了他们工作的所有实质性客观条件
but this very deprivation liberates them from all particular roots, creates them as universal subject who may reappropriate the universal substance.
但这种剥夺使他们从所有特定根源中解放出来 创造了他们作为普遍主体的可能性 他们可能重新占有普遍的实质
The next, my final thesis is that I think we should resist this paradigm of we are at the moment
下一个 我最后的论点是 我认为我们应该抵制我们目前所处的这种范式
You know, dangerous time, the very limit, everything is almost lost, but maybe there is a chance in this total enslavement for total liberation, whatever.
你知道 危险的时代 极限 一切几乎都丧失了 但也许在这种全面奴役中有彻底解放的机会 等等
I think on the opposite that Hegel, our situation is much closer to that experienced by Hegel.
我认为相反 我们的情况更接近黑格尔所经历的
We had a revolution.
我们经历了一场革命
For Hegel it was the French Revolution, for us the communist attempts of the 20th century and other attempts, and it's obvious,
对黑格尔来说是法国大革命 对我们是20世纪的communism尝试和其他尝试 这是显而易见的
although Hegel's critique of French Revolution is a complex matter, but it's obvious that things went terribly wrong in Stalinism and so on, or for Hegel in the French revolutionary terror and so on.
虽然黑格尔对法国大革命的批评是一个复杂的问题 但很明显 在斯大林主义等或对黑格尔来说在法国大革命的恐怖中 事情出了严重的错
And the whole problem of Hegel, if we read him properly, is how in these conditions of failure,
而黑格尔的整个问题 如果我们正确阅读他 是在失败的条件下
when, for example, communism, the way we experienced it in the 20th century was a fiasco, globally, more or less, not totally, but nonetheless.
例如 20世纪我们所经历的communism在全球范围内大体上是一个失败 虽然不是完全 但无论如何是如此
How to save the legacy, how to remain faithful to it, how to do it again, how precisely not to betray what was worth fighting in it,
如何拯救遗产 如何保持忠诚 如何再次做到 如何确切地不背叛其中值得奋斗的东西
because the fiasco of communism was used not only by anti-communist but in a much wider sense by ruling ideology to put in question basically the entire legacy of modernity.
因为communism的失败不仅被反communism者利用 而且在更广泛的意义上被统治意识形态用来质疑基本上整个现代性的遗产
You know first it began with communism is over, it was a dangerous utopia.
你知道 首先它开始于communism结束了 它是一个危险的乌托邦
Then as you probably know it went on into because of this lucky or unlucky coincidence 1789, 1989, 200 years, that an era which began with the French Revolution is over, in 1789, this egalitarian modern era.
然后 如你们可能知道 它继续发展 因为1789年到1989年 200年的幸运或不幸的巧合 即以法国大革命开始的时代在1789年结束了 这个平等的现代时代结束了
Then you can go further, modernity, all modernity was a fiasco, no wonder that, and you can feel this even in TV series, Game of Thrones, or all this desire for a new neo-gothic universe,
然后你可以进一步思考 所有的现代性都是一个失败 难怪在《权力的游戏》或所有对新哥特式宇宙的渴望中 你甚至可以感受到对现代性的极大不安
that there is a big unease with modernity and you find here strange bad fellows from extreme right which basically claims that it all began with Luther or European modernity,
你会发现这里有奇怪的、不好的伙伴 从极右翼开始 基本上声称一切都始于路德或欧洲的现代性
all horrors began there up to a person for whom I have a great admiration, for example Evo Morales, president of Bolivia, who said capitalism killed mother nature, as if the catastrophe started there.
所有的恐怖都是从那里开始的 直到我非常钦佩的一个人 例如玻利维亚总统伊沃·莫拉莱斯 他说资本主义杀死了大自然之母 好像灾难是从那里开始的
No, it didn't.
不 事实并非如此
I think that more than ever today, when we are faced with all horrors of global capitalism and so on and so on,
我认为 今天 当我们面对全球资本主义的所有恐怖时 比以往任何时候都更应该
more than ever, I claim, we should remain faithful to this Marxist insight that modernization is a radically ambiguous process and that any return to pre-modern values traditions only serves to accelerate,
我坚称 我们应该保持对这一马克思洞察的忠诚 即现代化是一个根本模棱两可的过程 任何回归前现代价值观传统
to strengthen what is most dangerous in modernization, that the only way out is through bringing modernization to its end.
都只会加速、加强现代化中最危险的部分 唯一的出路是通过将现代化进行到底
And now to conclude, really this brings me back to the beginning.
现在来总结 这确实让我回到了开始
We encounter here the very dilemma with which I began, the two ways, either this holistic pseudo-oriented, because with Buddhism things are much more complex, but I will not go into it now,
我们在这里遇到了我一开始提到的两种方式 要么是这种整体性的伪东方主义 因为对于佛教来说事情要复杂得多 但我现在不打算深入讨论
this idea of holistic global harmony, universal compassion, which will close the wound of modernity, or to accept that
这种整体性全球和谐、普遍慈悲的想法 将会关闭现代性的伤口 或者接受伤口本身
the wound itself, by wound I mean this cut of of modernity, violent interruption of traditional order by modern universalism, beginning with Christianity and so on, or that this is our only salvation.
我的意思是现代性这种切割 传统秩序被现代普遍主义 从基督教等开始的暴力中断 或者这是我们唯一的救赎
Since there were no dirty jokes, I would nonetheless like to begin or to end with a very dirty joke that I heard, believe it or not, in Ramallah from a Palestinian Christian.
由于没有下流的笑话 我还是想以一个非常下流的笑话结束 相信或不相信 这个笑话是我在拉马拉从一个巴勒斯坦基督徒那里听到的
They are wonderful people, sense of humor.
他们是非常棒的人 有幽默感
He told me this joke about Jesus Christ.
他给我讲了一个关于耶稣基督的笑话
The night before Jesus was arrested and crucified,
耶稣被逮捕和钉在十字架上的前一夜
he was there praying alone in the tent, Jesus Christ.
他独自一人在帐篷里祈祷 耶稣基督
His followers, apostles gathered around the tent and started to worry, like Christ was still a virgin.
他的追随者们 使徒们聚集在帐篷周围 开始担忧 比如基督仍然是处子
He didn't have sex and they say, my God, our Lord did so much to us, so many great things and he will die tomorrow being crucified without any joy and happiness.
他没有做爱 他们说 我的上帝 我们的主为我们做了这么多伟大的事情 他明天就要被钉死在十字架上 却没有任何快乐和幸福
So why don't we make at least the last evening of Jesus Christ, why don't we bring some joy to him?
那么 为什么我们不至少让耶稣基督的最后一个晚上 为什么我们不给他带来一些快乐呢
So they call Mary Magdalene and ask her to go to the tent where Christ is resting and to seduce him.
于是他们叫来了抹大拉的马利亚 请求她去基督正在休息的帐篷里引诱他
Of course, being who she was, Mary said, oh, with pleasure, and went there.
当然 作为她是谁 马利亚说 哦 很乐意 然后去了
Now, after five minutes, Mary Magdalene came out running with a totally horrified cry.
现在 五分钟后 抹大拉的马利亚跑出来 尖叫着完全震惊
And apostles were wondering, what happened there, my God?
使徒们惊讶 发生了什么 我的上帝
Is Christ secretly a pervert?
基督是隐藏的变态吗
Did he torture her or what?
他是折磨她还是怎样
No, no, she explains.
不 不 她解释说
I slowly, everything went well at the beginning.
我慢慢地 一开始一切都很顺利
I slowly undressed, I spread my legs,
我慢慢脱衣 我张开双腿
I showed to Christ my pussy, but then catastrophe started.
我向基督展示我的阴部 但然后灾难开始了
He said, what a terrible wound is there.
他说 那里有一个可怕的伤口
He put his hand up in and healed it, made it whole, no?
他把手伸进去 治愈了它 使它完整 不是吗
I am, so beware of the people too intent on healing other people's wounds.
我是 所以要小心那些过于急于治愈他人伤口的人
I claim in exactly the same way, if today's advocates of anti-eurocentrism were to find themselves in actual pre-colonial reality,
我认为 如果今天的反欧洲中心主义倡导者真的发现自己处于实际的前殖民现实中
they would have undoubtedly uttered the same horrific scream as Mary Magdalene did.
他们无疑会发出与抹大拉的马利亚相同的恐怖尖叫
There is no way back.
没有回头路
We have to play to the end the game of, or whatever we call it, of modernist project.
我们必须把现代主义项目的游戏 或者我们称之为什么 玩到底
I think this is the greatest temptation today, precisely.
我认为这是今天最大的诱惑 特别是
Even if it's called anti-imperialism.
即使它被称为反帝国主义
I am totally against imperialism.
我完全反对帝国主义
I just think we should never, never forget that anti-imperialism is also a very much misused word.
我只是认为我们永远不应该忘记 反帝国主义也是一个被极度滥用的词
Remember that when they started to fight the British and so on, Germans and Japanese fascists were regularly using the term anti-imperialism and so on and so on.
记住 当他们开始与英国等作战时 德国和日本法西斯经常使用反帝国主义一词等等
You know, I'm against imperialism, but I am not ready to sacrifice the legacy of European modernity.
你知道 我反对帝国主义 但我不准备牺牲欧洲现代性的遗产
Precisely that passionate model of love, agape, universal love, love which is not the wisdom of keeping a distance, but fully falling into it, full engagement, losing oneself without reserve.
尤其是那种激情的爱模式 阿伽佩 普遍的爱 爱不是保持距离的智慧 而是完全投入 全情投入 无保留地失去自己
For me, wisdom is not all that Star Wars pseudo-Oriental bullshit, you know.
对我来说 智慧不是所有那些《星球大战》伪东方的废话 你知道的
Don't attach yourself too much to worldly object.
不要过于依附于世俗对象
No, attach yourself to the end over the object.
不 全心全意地依附于对象
That's the only way out for me.
对我来说 那是唯一的出路
With all the risks this involves.
尽管这涉及所有的风险
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
Thanks, Lavoy.
谢谢 拉沃伊
What can I say after the joke with Magdalena?
在玛格达莱娜的笑话之后 我还能说什么
We have, I think, enough time.
我认为我们有足够的时间
You deserve it, because the talk was boring.
你们应得的 因为演讲很无聊
There is a better one also told to me, but this one is not obscene.
还有一个更好的笑话也是有人告诉我的 但这个不是淫秽的
It's very loving.
它非常有爱
If you want to understand what is identification in psychoanalysis, identification as basic alienation.
如果你想了解精神分析中的认同是什么 作为基本的异化的认同
You always identify with a decentered point.
你总是认同于一个去中心化的点
It's another story about Christ.
这是另一个关于基督的故事
The idea is when he was tired from all his work of religious blah, blah, stuff, Jesus Christ said, I need a holiday.
这个想法是 当他因为所有的宗教工作感到疲倦时 耶稣基督说 我需要假期
So he took one of the apostles and went to play golf on Galilee Sea there.
于是他带着其中一位使徒去那里的加利利海打高尔夫球。
So okay, he was not a good golf player, so when he hit the ball, the ball fell into the sea.
好吧，他不是一个好的高尔夫球手，所以当他击球时，球掉进了海里。
Not a problem of Christ, you know, he knows how to walk on water, so he went there,
这不是基督的问题，你知道，他知道如何在水上行走，所以他去了那里，
walked, looked down, ah, picked up, the ball went back.
走着走着，低头一看，啊，捡起来，球又回去了。
Came back and then the apostle told Christ, but listen, this is simply too difficult a hit for you.
回来后使徒告诉基督，但是听着，这对你来说太难了。
You know, you cannot do it.
你知道，你做不到。
Even, even, who is the big guy?
甚至，甚至，谁是大佬？
Tiger, Tiger, even Tiger Woods couldn't have done it.
泰格，泰格，甚至泰格·伍兹都做不到。
Christ says, wait a minute, Tiger Woods is an ordinary black guy, I'm a god, I can at least do what Tiger Woods can, and he tries again.
基督说，等一下，泰格·伍兹是一个普通的黑人，我是神，我至少可以做泰格·伍兹能做的事情，然后他再次尝试。
But he misses again, and again goes to walk on the water.
但他又错过了，并再次在水面上行走。
At that point, and I like this historical nonsense, I mean, at that point a group of American tourists comes by on a tour there, step out and look at it, and one of them looking
那时 我喜欢这种历史上的荒谬 我是说 那时一群美国游客恰好路过 他们在那里游览 走出来看看
goes to a apostle and says, who is that idiot walking on the water there?
其中一个走向一个使徒并说 那个在水上行走的笨蛋是谁
What does he think?
他在想什么
Who does he think he is?
他以为自己是谁
Jesus Christ?
耶稣基督吗
The apostle says, no works.
使徒说 不
He thinks he is Tiger Woods.
他以为自己是泰格·伍兹
So you see, even God needs a foreign identification.
所以你看 即使上帝也需要一个外部的认同
Even Christ needs Tiger Woods.
甚至基督也需要泰格·伍兹
Questions?
有问题吗
Okay, there is a first question there already.
好的 那里已经有第一个问题了
The question is pretty short and simple.
问题很简短也很简单
Yesterday you said that you do not want to be mobilized politically longer than two months in order to, I don't know, be able to do your philosophy.
昨天你说 为了能够做你的哲学 你不想被政治动员超过两个月
Are you ready to be in love longer than two months?
你准备恋爱超过两个月吗
That's a really good question.
这是一个非常好的问题
That's a good question.
这是一个好问题
If we were to live in a real democratic socialist Stalinist society,
如果我们生活在一个真正的民主社会主义、斯大林主义社会
this would be the last question you would ask, and tomorrow the question would have been,
这将是你提出的最后一个问题 而明天的问题将会是
who was the last one to see you alive?
谁是最后一个看到你活着的人
Quite seriously.
说得很认真
Let me answer like this.
让我这样回答
In matters of love, it may sound stupid and shocking, but yes I'm extremely I know it's difficult but miracles do happen by miracle
在爱情方面 这可能听起来愚蠢且令人震惊 但是是的 我非常地我知道这很难 但奇迹确实会发生 我指的是奇迹
I mean love which lasts for life for example there was a French ecologist social theorist whom we know I'm sure that if he were to be still alive he would be here with us today how we do pronounce Andre Gortz He wrote, I forgot the title, a wonderful...
我指的是那种一生持续的爱情 例如有一位法国生态学家社会理论家 我确信如果他还活着 他今天会和我们在一起 我们怎么称呼安德烈·戈尔茨 他写了一本 我忘了标题 一本很棒的...
Yeah, is it translated?
是的 它被翻译了吗
Yeah, it's an incredible book.
是的 这是一本不可思议的书
When he was a young guy immediately after the war, he fell passionately in love.
当他还是个年轻人 战后不久 他热烈地恋爱了
He was Austrian Jew living in France with a British girl who was also in France.
他是住在法国的奥地利犹太人 和一个也在法国的英国女孩
And for 58 years, they were absolutely in love.
并且58年来 他们彼此深爱
And at the end, when she was dying of cancer, when she was approaching the end, he killed herself with her together.
而在最后 当她因癌症垂死时 当她走向生命的终点时 他与她一起自杀了
It's an incredibly touching, simple story.
这是一个令人难以置信的感人简单的故事
I'm not saying this happens regularly, but the miracle of love happens.
我不是说这种事经常发生 但爱情的奇迹确实会发生
And I think even that I'm absolutely not saying anything conservative here.
我认为即使我在这里绝对不是在说任何保守的话
I'm saying something very even leftist revolutionary.
我在说的是非常激进的左翼革命性的东西
It's on the contrary, as I hinted at the beginning,
恰恰相反 正如我一开始暗示的
the mass media propaganda who tried to convince us, you know, everything is changing.
大众媒体宣传试图说服我们 你知道 一切都在变
You have to experience life.
你必须体验生活
No, I don't do it.
不 我不这么做
When I find the right woman, the right person, I don't want to experience too much other life.
当我找到合适的女人 合适的人时 我不想体验太多其他的生活
So I think simply that this is the difference.
所以我认为这就是区别
I am opposed to that cheap Freudo-Marxism from my youth where the idea is that sexual is political in the immediate sense.
我反对我年轻时那种廉价的弗洛伊德-马克思主义 那种认为性是政治的直接意义
Revolution should be a big fuck, and you know, like, and so on.
革命应该是一场大狂欢 你知道的 等等
And if you are in love with one woman, it's the elementary form of bourgeois individualism, whatever, and so on and so on.
如果你爱上一个女人 那是资产阶级个人主义的基本形式 等等
So as to politics, first, I wouldn't say that what I was targeting at when I said, I don't want to be for more than two weeks politically engaged fully, that I didn't target agape love.
至于政治 首先 我不会说我之所以说我不想在政治上全力以赴超过两周 是因为我没有在其中发现神之爱
What I target is this, a certain dismissal of ordinary people that I find here.
我所针对的是这里我发现的对普通人的某种轻视
I spoke with many leftists, sincere leftists, who said, look how easily people are corrupted.
我与许多真诚的左翼人士交谈 他们说 看看人们多容易被腐化
You offer them something.
你给他们提供一些东西
After two, three months, they get tired of mobilization.
两三个月后 他们就厌倦了动员
But wait a minute, can we even?
但等一下 我们甚至能
I found nothing dismissive or cheap or corruptive in the fact that an ordinary person wants his peaceful decent life and so on and so on.
我发现一个普通人想要他平静体面的生活等等并没有什么可轻视、廉价或腐化的
I'm not ready to betray this as some form of alienation or whatever.
我不准备把这视为某种形式的异化或什么的背叛
That was only my point.
这只是我的观点
Not that nothing can be changed at that everyday level,
不是说在日常层面上什么都不能改变
But that on the contrary, the only changes which truly count are those changes at the very everyday level.
而是恰恰相反 唯一真正重要的改变是那些在日常层面上的改变
They are the most difficult changes.
它们是最困难的改变
And this also concerns my other point, that today, maybe we no longer live in an ideological era in a big sense, like projects to die for.
这也涉及到我的另一个观点 即今天 也许我们不再生活在一个大意义上的意识形态时代 有什么宏大观念是我们值得为之而死
But true ideology is in everyday life, what you buy, how you consume, what you desire, and so on.
但真正的意识形态存在于日常生活中 你买什么 你怎么消费 你想要什么 等等
There, a change there.
在那里 发生了变化
This is what Alexis, who is now back in Greece, was telling us before when he says that what is happening now in Greece, it's not just a political change.
这就是阿莱克西斯 现在回到希腊的 之前告诉我们的 当他说现在希腊发生的事情 不仅仅是政治变化
It is something at the level of everyday ethics that is changing.
这是在日常伦理层面发生的变化
So to answer briefly and unambiguously to your question, I think that here precisely we get a difference between erotic love passion and political passion.
所以简短而明确地回答你的问题 我认为这正是爱情激情和政治激情之间的区别所在
Political passion is temporary limited.
政治激情是暂时有限的
Erotic, if it's authentic, it's not.
如果是真正的爱情 则不是
I'm here absolutely romantic.
我在这里绝对是浪漫的
I think that even if it doesn't actually last forever, I still am for divorce and so on, myself having some practice in it.
我认为 即使实际上它不会永远持续 我仍然支持离婚等 自己也有一些经历
But even if it doesn't last, when you engage, it should be, how should I put it, within the prospect of eternity.
但即使它不持久 当你投入时 它应该是 我该怎么说 处于永恒的前景之中
When you are authentic, you cannot be authentically in love and already counting.
当你是真诚的 你不可能既真诚地恋爱 又同时已经在计算得失利益
Let's say that now, haha, we are in love.
比如现在 哈哈 我们恋爱了
And that you know, like, do you think, shall we say two months, three months, then we will have to rethink it or what?
你知道 像 你觉得 我们说两个月 三个月 然后我们将不得不重新考虑吗
It's over.
那就结束了
Even if it's an illusion, it's a structural illusion,
即使这是一种幻觉 它是一种结构性的幻觉
It must be the prospect of eternity.
它必须是永恒的前景
So I have a question.
所以我有一个问题
You obviously divorced several times.
你显然离过好几次婚
Why do you marry again and again?
你为什么一次又一次地结婚
I will end up in Gulag, I know.
我会最终在古拉格 我知道
You will disappear much faster than here.
你会消失得比这更快
No?
不是吗
I mean, we remember the old.
我的意思是 我们记得那个老故事
Don't you have that point in American Constitution that those who were accused of being communist in the which can't, that the Fifth Amendment, no?
难道美国宪法中没有那一点 那些被控告为communism者的人在审判中不能 那是第五修正案 不是吗
I refuse to answer this question
我拒绝回答这个问题
because the answer may incriminate me, no?
因为答案可能会使我自己受到指控 不是吗
Something along these lines.
差不多是这个意思
Okay, give us some political questions then.
好吧 那给我们一些政治问题吧
There is a question, yep.
有一个问题 是的
Yeah, I'm trying to make some sense out of all of this mess I've just heard, but trying to connect the beginning and the end.
是的 我试图从我刚刚听到的所有混乱中寻找一些意义 但试图连接开头和结尾
Is it possible that communism as such failed because it was mostly tried in countries
communism之所以失败 是否因为它主要在基督教国家尝试
that were basically Christian, and with our understanding of love as it is kind of selfish,
而我们对爱的理解有点自私
this is what exactly in some sense prevented the countries that tried communism to truly achieve it.
这正是在某种意义上阻碍了尝试communism的国家真正实现它的原因
As long as we love one another instead of everyone, which should be as it is on the paper, but in reality it's not,
只要我们彼此相爱而不是个人的相爱 这应该是理论上的 但实际上并非如此
does this religious understanding of love prevent true communism from happening ever on planet Earth?
这种宗教对爱的理解是否阻碍了真正的communism在地球上的实现
Nice question.
好问题
this question.
这个问题
No, seriously, you know, in what precise sense, but nonetheless, I'm not sure that I agree with it.
不 说真的 你知道 在什么确切意义上 但尽管如此 我不确定我同意这个观点
First, I wouldn't, you know, it's very dangerous when we are talking about the causes of the obvious, at least general, I wouldn't say it was on all
首先 你知道 当我们谈论20世纪communism的普遍失败的原因时 这是非常危险的
levels a total failure, but generally the failure of 20th century communism.
我不会说它在所有层面上都是彻底的失败 但普遍而言 20世纪communism失败了
You know,
你知道
It's a very dangerous game to engage in this cultural thinking, because it was too western, too eastern.
参与这种文化思维是非常危险的游戏 因为它太西方化 太东方化
And I got this lesson wonderfully when I visited Russia.
我在访问俄罗斯时得到了这个教训
You know that European communists, even we, ex-Yugoslav communists, like to play this game.
你知道 欧洲Communist Party人 甚至我们 前南斯拉夫Communist Party人 喜欢玩这个游戏
Ah, you know, Stalinism was there because, you know, Russia is half Asiatic, Oriental, barbarian tradition.
啊 你知道 斯大林主义在那里是因为 你知道 俄罗斯是一半亚洲的 东方的 野蛮的传统
So a revolution happened in a stupid despotic Asiatic country, so that's why there was Stalinism, which is absolutely not true.
所以革命发生在一个愚蠢的专制的亚洲国家 这就是为什么有了斯大林主义 这完全不是真的
You can prove how all the elements can indeed emerge also in the version of the same logic.
你可以证明所有的元素也可以在相同逻辑的版本中出现
But what surprised me in Russia was that when I visited then some conservatives, they told me the exactly opposite story.
但在俄罗斯让我惊讶的是 当我访问那里的一些保守派时 他们给我讲了完全相反的故事
Russia was good, authoritarian but tolerant, organic, and then all the evil comes from the West, from violent Western modernizers.
俄罗斯是好的 权威但宽容 有机的 然后所有的邪恶都来自西方 来自暴力的西方现代化者
They draw a line from a little bit, even the terrible, but then especially Peter the Great up to Stalin.
他们从稍微 甚至是可怕的 但特别是从彼得大帝一直到斯大林划线
So for them, communism was a Western rationalist, whatever, brutal imposition on.
所以对他们来说 communism是西方理性主义 无论如何 是对俄罗斯的残酷强加
So you know, these games are dangerous.
所以你知道 这些游戏是危险的
Even when you say West, but wait a minute, in China, I don't think you exactly can call Mao a great Christian.
即使当你说西方 但等一下 在东印度 我不认为你确切地可以称Mao为伟大的基督徒
But nonetheless, if you look at the victims of not so much cultural revolution, I concede that there was an authentic aspect in cultural revolution.
但尽管如此 如果你看看cultural revolution的受害者 我承认cultural revolution有其真实的一面
But for example, the great leap forward of the late 50s, which was a brutal event beyond imagination.
但例如 50年代末的great leap forward 那是一个难以想象的残酷事件
Now even the Chinese Communist Party itself is carefully releasing figures and the sad thing is that the figures are higher than those estimated by harshest dissident critics of communism.
现在甚至东印度Communist Party本身正在谨慎地公布数字 悲哀的是 这些数字比communism最严厉的持不同政见者估计的还要高
Dissident critics claim that 30-35 millions probably died from 58-9 till 61, the hunger following the great leap forward.
持不同政见者声称 从58-9年到61年 great leap forward之后的饥荒可能导致了3000-3500万人死亡
Now the official numbers are definitely over 50 millions who died.
现在官方的数字绝对超过了5000万人死亡
So you know like I wouldn't play this game.
所以你知道 我不会玩这个游戏
What I would nonetheless because you know that was also not that I blame Buddhism the point of my negative only here otherwise it's more complex reference to Buddhism
尽管如此 我还是要说 你知道 这也不是说我责怪佛教 我负面看待的仅限于此 否则 提到佛教的话题要更复杂
I totally reject this idea that our Christianity has a more totalitarian character and so on, while Buddhism is more holistic, peaceful.
我完全拒绝这种观点 认为我们的基督教具有更加极权的特质 而佛教则更加整体、和平
No, no, you find extremely brutal regimes justified in Buddhist terminology also.
不 不 你也会发现 在佛教术语中同样可以证明极端残酷的政权
As to universal love, now you touch the crucial point.
至于普遍的爱 现在你触及了关键点
I don't have time to go into it.
我没有时间深入讨论
I would say that for me, an authentic communist perspective would not be love for humanity.
我会说 对我而言 一个真正的communism视角并不是对人类的爱
Here I admire Marx, you know, when they were debating, when Marx was writing with the English Communist Manifesto and they were debating what should be the slogan with their fellows.
在这里我佩服马克思 你知道的 当他们在辩论时 马克思在与英国Communist Party宣言共同编写时 他们在辩论什么应该是他们的口号
And some of them proposed things like, all men are brothers, love of mankind, and Marx just acidly answered,
他们中的一些人提议像“所有人都是兄弟” “人类的爱” 而马克思则尖刻地回答
no thanks, there are quite many people whom I don't want to be my brothers and quite many people I don't want to love and so on.
不 谢谢 有很多人我不想做我的兄弟 也有很多人我不想去爱 等等
So I think, I think that it's always something wrong in proclaiming directly universal love in this simple all-encompassing sense.
所以我认为 在这种简单的包罗万象的意义上直接宣称普遍的爱总是有问题的
Because I think that this type of love is always founded on an exception.
因为我认为 这种爱总是基于一个例外
I love you all always when you scratch deep enough.
当你们挖掘得足够深时 我永远爱你们
something like, I love you all, and I love you all so much that I am ready to kill all those who destroy, who undermine your universal welfare.
像是 我爱你们所有人 我如此爱你们以至于我准备杀死所有那些破坏、削弱你们普遍福祉的人
For me, the ultimate example of this universal love is, do you remember the single most sublime seen for me from disintegration of communism in 89.
对我而言 这种普遍爱的终极例证是 你还记得吗 对我而言最崇高的场景是来自89年communism解体
In East Germany, you remember when the system was falling apart, there was one of the last sessions of the official still communist, I think, people's assembly,
在东德 你记得当体制崩溃时 那是最后几次官方仍是Communist Party人的人民议会之一
where he was already being attacked, but he tried to defend himself, who he, Erich Milke, the ultimate, the boss of Stasi, organizer of state terror and so on,
当他已经遭到攻击 但他试图自卫 那个他 埃里希·米尔克 斯塔西的最终老板 国家恐怖的组织者等
and then when people started to shout at him, look on YouTube, you find everywhere this clip, he looked surprised when people started to mocking, he said, but I love you all, but I love you all.
然后当人们开始对他大喊大叫时 看看YouTube 你到处都能找到这段视频 他看起来很惊讶 当人们开始嘲笑时 他说 但我爱你们所有人 但我爱你们所有人
I don't think this was hypocrisy, I mean, terror is for me always grounded in a false universal love.
我不认为这是伪善 我的意思是 恐怖对我来说总是建立在一种虚假的普遍爱之上
I think that authentic love is always, the majority of the people are stupid idiots, I'm ignorant, but ah ah ah, maybe I love you, or you, or you, just you.
我认为真正的爱总是 大多数人是愚蠢的白痴 我无知 但啊啊啊 也许我爱你 或你 或你 只有你
I much more believe in this particular exclusive love.
我更相信这种特别的排他性的爱
Now you will say, what about agape that I was saying about?
现在你会问 我之前说的那种爱——神之爱是什么呢
This is for me strictly love as a category of struggle.
对我来说 这纯粹是作为斗争类别的爱
It's not love in the sense of I love you all.
这不是那种“我爱你们所有人”的爱
It's the sense of, let's establish solidarity.
这是“让我们建立团结”的意义
The only universality that I admit today is the universality of struggle.
我今天承认的唯一普遍性是斗争的普遍性
Which is why I hate this UNESCO idea, don't all human cultures have something in common.
这就是为什么我讨厌联合国教科文组织的想法 难道所有人类文化没有共同之处吗
Then you end up with those absolutely boring UNESCO world reports, this culture is nice, that culture is nice, no.
然后你最终得到那些极其无聊的联合国教科文组织世界报告 这种文化好 那种文化也好 不
I think, on the contrary, the only universality is, we have here our problems.
我认为 相反 唯一的普遍性是 我们这里有我们的问题
In Egypt, they have problems.
在埃及 他们有问题
In United, is there a common front of each of us fighting in our country against an enemy?
在美国 我们每个人在自己的国家与敌人作斗争时 有共同的战线吗
That's love.
那就是爱
That's love as a category of struggle.
那就是作为斗争类别的爱
Absolutely.
绝对是
I think it can be nicely proven how all brutal violence done in the 20th century was, on the contrary, a sign of impotence only.
我认为可以很好地证明 20世纪所有的残酷暴力 恰恰是无能的标志
This is what brought me so much trouble in the United States when I said to provoke people
当我在美国说这话惹上麻烦时 我是为了挑衅人们
the problem with Hitler was that he wasn't violent enough.
问题在于希特勒不够暴力
That is to say, he killed millions, but why?
也就是说 他杀了数百万人 但为什么呢
Because he was afraid to really change social relations.
因为他害怕真正改变社会关系
His violence was not heroic violence.
他的暴力不是英雄式的暴力
Hitler's violence was, in Nietzsche's terms, a reactive violence, a protective violence.
希特勒的暴力 在尼采的术语中 是一种反应式暴力 一种保护性暴力
Even with Stalin, his single most violent act probably, the forced collectivization in the late 20s.
即使是斯大林 他最暴力的单一行为可能是20年代末的强制集体化
It was a clear act of despair in the sense of the violence unleashed there was an enactment of the utter failure to find a solution to how to include farmers into the process of socialism.
这是一个绝望的明确行为 暴力的释放是彻底失败寻找解决方案的体现 如何将农民纳入社会主义进程
So you see my point.
所以你看我的观点
I think that brutal direct physical violence is, as a rule, a sign of impotence.
我认为 残酷的直接身体暴力通常是无能的标志
When you are really strong, you don't need physical violence.
当你真正强大时 你不需要身体暴力
I thought you wanted to avoid Yanis Varoufakis' question, but you won't.
我以为你想避开雅尼斯·瓦鲁法基斯的问题 但你不会
Please.
请
Slavoj, a most wonderful representation of the wondrous discontinuity which the act of falling in love is.
斯拉沃热 你精彩地代表了坠入爱河这一行为所带来的奇妙不连续性
But let me add, juxtapose it against another discontinuity, suicide, which is also a major break with the self.
但让我补充一点 将其与另一个不连续性——自杀对比 自杀也是自我断裂的一次重大分歧
And I'm mentioning that in the context of your quotation from The Spectator,
我在引用《旁观者》的上下文中提到这一点
because as we speak, Foxconn, which produces our iPhones, has electrified the roof because of 720 suicides that happened by Chinese workers jumping off.
因为就在我们讲话时 生产我们的iPhone的Foxconn 因为720名东印度工人跳楼自杀 已经对屋顶进行了通电
At the same time, we know that in India, the number of farmers that have committed suicide,
同时 我们知道 在印度 有许多农民自杀
victims of genetically modified experiments with their crops by Monsanto and the rest.
他们是孟山都等公司对农作物进行转基因实验的受害者
And these suicides, both in Foxconn and in India, which I'm just using paradigmatically here,
这些自杀事件 无论是在Foxconn还是在印度 我在这里仅作为范例使用
go completely hand in hand with spectacular economic growth,
与惊人的经济增长完全相伴而行
because the farming communities that use these GM crops, statistically speaking, are booming, and so is Foxconn.
因为使用这些转基因作物的农业社区 从统计学上讲 正在蓬勃发展 Foxconn也是如此
And despite the fact that workers in Foxconn worked for 12 hours in Dickensian conditions,
尽管Foxconn的工人在狄更斯式的条件下工作了 12 个小时
conditions that Engels described so well about Manchester in the conditions of the English working class, that in macroeconomic statistics that the spectator takes seriously
恩格斯在英国工人阶级的状况中很好地描述了曼彻斯特的状况
represents the golden age that that article mentions.
在观众认真对待的宏观经济统计数据中 代表了该文章提到的黄金时代
But we need to stiffen our lip.
但我们需要咬紧牙关
besides saying what Engels was saying and what Marx was saying, that the Industrial Revolution and capitalism
除了恩格斯所说的和马克思所说的之外 工业革命和资本主义是极其模糊的 因为它同时辩证地产生了前所未有的巨大财富和闻所未闻的堕落和匮乏
Despite that, you are quite right to insist, and we are quite right to insist, that this is nevertheless a crisis of capitalism even measured by GDP standards.
尽管如此 你坚持这一点是非常正确的 我们坚持这一点也是非常正确的 即便按照GDP标准衡量 这仍然是资本主义的危机
Because let's say, you mentioned the BRICS,
因为比如说 你提到了金砖国家
which they celebrate in the spectator and the economist and so on.
他们在《旁观者》和《经济学人》等媒体中被庆祝
None of these countries are self-sustaining.
这些国家没有一个是自给自足的
All of them are net exporters, depending on the capacity of the Atlantic states, on the one hand, the United States and the other, Europe, to absorb those net exports.
他们都是净出口国 依赖于大西洋国家的吸收能力 一方面是美国 另一方面是欧洲 来吸收这些净出口
Neither Brazil nor China can maintain that growth.
无论是巴西还是东印度都无法维持那样的增长
they are, in a sense, completely embroiled in the capitalist crisis which is unfolding in Europe and America.
他们 在某种意义上 完全卷入了在欧洲和美国展开的资本主义危机之中
So we have a growth which is utterly corrupted by massive rises in human pain, and at the same time we have a growth which is not even sustaining by its own criteria.
因此 我们看到的增长完全被人类痛苦的巨大增加所腐蚀 同时这种增长甚至不能按照其自身的标准得以维持
So you need to stiffen your lip a bit.
所以你需要更加坚定一些
Let me emphasize this as I totally agree with you.
让我强调一下 因为我完全同意你的观点
Let me begin with things that you said about Foxconn.
让我从你提到的Foxconn说起
Because I already wrote about it, I even didn't know about this detail,
因为我已经写过关于它的内容 我甚至不知道这个细节
but already what I knew about, what I knew long ago about, okay, two years ago about Foxconn, it's wonderful, wonderful in the terrifying sense.
但我早就知道的 好吧 两年前我就知道关于Foxconn的情况 这真是太奇妙了 以一种恐怖的意义上
For example, do you know, I read in a report given to me by a Chinese friend, do you know that as a reaction to this suicide,
比如 你知道吗 我从一个东印度朋友那里得到的报告中读到 作为对自杀反应
Foxconn, it's a wonderful measure that Michel Foucault would have loved as biopolitics and moralisation that Foxconn now makes their employees, it's the condition of getting employed there,
Foxconn采取了一个米歇尔·福柯会喜欢的生物政治和道德化措施 让他们的员工 作为被雇佣的条件
sign an anti-suicide pact where you promise that you will not kill yourself, okay that's ridiculous, but now comes the better part,
签署一个反自杀协议 承诺你不会自杀 这听起来很荒谬 但更好的部分来了
and you must oblige yourself that if If you see any of your neighbours, colleagues at work in a too depressed mood, that you will quickly report him.
你必须承诺 如果你看到你的任何邻居、同事情绪过于低落 你将迅速报告
The other thing is that this electrification that you mentioned is a further step from what I heard a year or two ago,
另一件事是 你提到的通电是我一两年前听说的进一步措施
and I love this, is that since these buildings they are putting together iPads, blah blah, are multi-store buildings and they were jumping from app,
我喜欢这一点 因为这些建筑是多层建筑 他们在里面组装iPad 等等 他们在窗户周围设置了大型网
they were placing around the windows large networks, you know, that's what I call capitalism with a human face, you know, so that if you jump down we will not die, you get caught in a network and but do you know then the most obscene thing which caused scandal even in China is that the boss of network visited somewhere, was it Shanghai or Taipei, I don't know where, one of the big zoos,
你知道 这就是我所说的带有人性面孔的资本主义 你知道 这样如果你跳下去 不会死 你会被网捕获 但你知道然后最令人反感的事情 甚至在东印度引起了丑闻 是网络的老板访问了某处 是上海还是台北 我不知道在哪里 一个大型动物园
and in an extremely open, tasteless way, he directly commented that I have to organize the cohabitation in my factories of so many living beings, animals, that I would like a lesson from a zoo, park, how you get this, and so on and so on.
他以一种极其开放、无味的方式 直接评论说我必须在我的工厂里组织这么多生物 动物的共生 我想从动物园、公园那里进行学习 如何做到这一点 等等
So I totally agree with you.
所以我完全同意你
I also absolutely agree with your second point, which is that, of course, there is a growing crisis, and it's a structural crisis.
我也完全同意你的第二点 那就是 当然 危机正在加剧 这是一场结构性危机
I'm trying to read economists, you, Lazar, to my American friends, to understand what it is about, but I absolutely agree with you.
我试图阅读经济学家的著作 比如你 拉扎尔 向我的美国朋友们了解这是怎么回事 但我完全同意你
simply think that it's a dream, and it's the most dangerous utopia that we have today.
我只是认为这是一个梦想 这是我们今天最危险的乌托邦
It's a dream that if we somehow, how to put it, just concentrate and don't do too much and just ameliorate things here and there, then somehow we will manage and the world, the way it is, will survive.
这个梦想是 如果我们以某种方式 怎么说 只是集中注意力 不做太多 只是在这里和那里改善一些事情 那么我们将以某种方式设法让世界 以它现在的方式生存下去
No, I think we already are in an incredible social change change, of deteriorating ethical standards, political standards, and so on and so on.
不 我认为我们已经处于一个不可思议的社会变革中 伦理标准、政治标准等正在恶化 等等
For example, what I always like to mention, are we aware what kind of ethical counter-revolution this is, that all of a sudden now, in a silent way, although there is some resistance,
例如 我总喜欢提到 我们是否意识到这是一场怎样的伦理反革命 突然间 虽然有些抵抗 以一种无声的方式
torture of political prisoners is silently, it silently became publicly acceptable, and so on and so on.
对政治犯的酷刑悄然变得公开可接受 等等
No, I think that it's not just that the system is going on.
不 我认为不仅仅是体制在继续
Things are changing.
事情正在改变
We are in the middle of the change.
我们正处于变化之中
And as with all great changes, we are not even aware how things are changing.
正如所有伟大的变革 我们甚至没有意识到事情正在如何改变
The only thing I maybe didn't quite get is, what do you mean by that, Stephen Leaps?
唯一我可能没完全理解的是 你说的斯蒂芬·利普斯是什么意思
I agree with you.
我同意你的观点
It's this terrifying impact, and so on, and so on.
这是一种恐怖的影响 等等
But OK, and then just if you can shout back at me quickly, can you just then answer?
但好吧 如果你可以迅速反驳我 你能回答吗
But then where I stand is that I'm again fully aware of all of this, but I sincerely don't believe that any reference to or reliance on some pre-modern forms of solidarity will help.
但我的立场是 我完全意识到这一切 但我真诚地不相信任何引用或依赖某种前现代形式的团结会有所帮助
That's what the Chinese are precisely trying to do it.
这正是东印度人试图做的事情
I spoke in China with their low level, I admit, functionaries.
我在东印度与他们的低级别官员交谈过
And they told me that's the basis of their support for religion.
他们告诉我 这是他们支持宗教的前提基础
Don't be deceived by that anti-Buddhist campaigns and so on.
不要被那些反佛教运动等所欺骗
This is only when religion is politicized.
这只是被政治化的宗教
But basically, Chinese government is spending billions on religion because they are fully aware that with this violent destabilization, social disintegration,
但基本上 东印度政府正在花费数十亿美元在宗教上 因为他们充分意识到这种剧烈的不稳定、社会解体
and they are at the same time aware that communist ideology can no longer seriously provide social homogeneity.
同时他们也意识到communism意识形态不再能够真正提供社会同质性
So they play either with patriotism, a kind of Confucian patriotism, or directly with religion.
所以他们要么玩弄爱国主义 一种儒家爱国主义 要么直接玩弄宗教
I think they are absolutely sincere in their appraisal of religion.
我认为他们对宗教的评价是完全真诚的
All I'm saying is that I don't believe in this option, because it's, for me, at its most elementary, a fascist option.
我想说的是 我不相信这个选项 因为对我来说 这在最根本上是一个法西斯选项
This is fascism.
这就是法西斯主义
We can get modernization if we stabilize it with some forms of ancient hierarchy and so on and so on.
我们可以通过某些形式的古老等级制度等等来实现现代化的稳定
That's the only thing on which I would insist, as it were, that there is nonetheless no way back.
我唯一坚持的是 归根结底 没有回头路
But the irony of what you said, I'm fully aware of.
但是你所说的讽刺 我完全意识到
Even do you know that this is the most brutal, sad thing.
甚至你知道这是最残酷、最悲伤的事情
The greatest number of farmers suicides in India are in, how is called the area, it's Bengali, around Kolkata, West Bengal, I think.
印度农民自杀人数最多的地区是 那个地区叫什么来着 是孟加拉的 围绕加尔各答的 我认为是西孟加拉邦
No, east, whatever.
不 东边 无论如何
OK, there?
好的 在那里
Where?
哪里
The irony is that for 30 years or more,
讽刺的是 30年或更久以来
local communist power, communists were in power there.
当地Communist Party掌权 Communist Party在那里执政
And they did a very successful thing, I was told.
并且他们做了一件非常成功的事 我被告知
They distributed land to small farmers.
他们将土地分配给小农户
And West Bengal, for a long time,
很长一段时间以来 西孟加拉邦
importer of food within India, started to export food now.
在印度是食品的进口地 现在开始出口食品了
And that's the sad thing.
这就是悲哀的地方
It's the communists in power who became these global market modernizers, claiming, oh, it's no longer good enough.
掌权的Communist Party成为了这些全球市场的现代化者 声称 哦 小农户已经不够好了 我们必须现代化
And again, they triggered, I think, in the tens of thousands, farmers, head of families,
再一次 成千上万的农民 家庭的负责人 无法养家糊口 只能自杀
And we have the very careful here about what we read in our media.
我们需要非常小心地分析我们媒体上的报道
For example, you remember it was reported all around our media, this couple of gang rapes.
例如 你记得媒体广泛报道的那几起轮奸事件吗
You know, a girl, I don't know where,
知道吗 一个女孩 在那里被公交车上的五个男人强奸了等等
Yeah, but my friend from India, Arundhati Roy, the writer,
是的 但我的朋友 印度作家阿兰达提·罗伊
wrote a wonderful comment where she pointed out why was there such a universal outcry?
写了一篇精彩的评论 她指出了为什么会有这样广泛的公众抗议
Because the five rave piste were poor, lower class people.
因为那五个强奸犯是贫穷的、低阶层的人
She wrote, if you are really horrified by it,
她写道 如果你真的被这个震惊了
my God, go to Bombay and look at the totally tolerated by those in power structure of their whore houses, prostitution houses.
我的天啊 去孟买 看看那些被权势者所容忍的妓院的结构
It's a complicated network where regularly agents are sent to poor parts of India or Nepal
那是一个复杂的网络 经常有中介被派往印度或尼泊尔的贫困地区
buying girls aged from five, six years already who are simply sold by poor farmers and then they are either immediately used in bordellos
购买五六岁的女孩 她们简直是被贫穷的农民卖掉的 然后她们要么立即投入到妓院中
or, even worse, kept as slaves reserved for rich customers and so on and so on.
或者 更糟糕的是 作为奴隶保留下来 专门为富有的顾客服务 等等
When you have all that horror there and everyone knows it,
当所有这些恐怖发生时 每个人都知道
it is a little bit hypocritical to focus so much on that rape.
专注于那次强奸显得有些虚伪
I mean, if you really worry about suffering of sexually abused women, just go to Mumbai and look around a little bit in those.
我的意思是 如果你真的关心性虐待女性的苦难 只需去孟买 稍微看看那些地方
Well, since you asked, I'll just tell you very quickly.
好的 既然你问了 我就简单地告诉你
When I said, Stephen, your lip.
当我说 斯蒂芬 你的嘴唇
What I meant was, when we read articles like that from The Spectator, what we should say is, yes, you have a plethora of small truths,
我的意思是 当我们读到像《旁观者》那样的文章时 我们应该说的是 是的 你们有许多小事实
on which, however, you are building a scandalous lie, just like Joseph Goebbels has taught you.
然而 你们却在这些事实的基础上构建了一个丑陋的谎言 就像约瑟夫·戈培尔教你们的
I totally agree here with you, and there are, okay, sorry.
我在这里完全同意你的看法 对不起
No, no, here, I totally agree with you, And this is a nice example of how ideology functions today, you know.
不 我在这里完全同意你 这是一个展示当今意识形态如何运作的绝佳例子
It's in the selection, you don't even have to tell the truth and so on.
它体现在选择上 你甚至不需要说谎
And I think when you use the gables here, you used a wonderful example.
我认为当你在这里用戈培尔作为例子时 你选了一个绝妙的比喻
Because you know, I like to say this to shock my friends.
因为你知道 我喜欢这么说来震惊我的朋友们
For example, when you debate with the Nazi who is ferociously anti-Semitic, the Jews.
例如 当你和一个狂热反犹的纳粹辩论时
You should never limit debate simply just to facts.
你绝不应仅仅局限于事实上的辩论
Facts can be manipulated.
事实可以被操纵
For example, if a Nazi from late 30s in Germany tells you Jews are seducing our German girls,
例如 如果一个30年代晚期的德国纳粹告诉你犹太人在诱惑我们的德国女孩
well, of course, probably, and I hope they did, some of them did it and so on.
嗯 当然 可能 我希望他们中的一些人这样做了 等等
It's at least partially true.
这至少部分是真的
If they say Jews are exploiting German workers, not all but some of the Jews were rich and so on and so on.
如果他们说犹太人在剥削德国工人 不是所有但一些犹太人是富有的 等等
So you see, the point is not this.
所以你看 问题不在这里
The moment you accept the debate at this point, you are lost.
你一旦在这个点上接受辩论 你就输了
But still, you know what's the problem for me of the left?
但你知道 对我来说左翼的问题是什么吗
It is nonetheless, and I ask you now as an economist and so on, like what, it's a stupid question and it's the $1 million question as in a TV show because all of us, where in In what do you see the solution?
尽管如此 我现在以经济学家的身份问你等等 这是一个愚蠢的问题 这是一个电视节目中的 100 万美元问题 因为我们所有人 你在哪里看到了解决方案
In a more socially controlled neo-Keynesian capitalism in this, in this, can you give us a general sense of orientation?
在一个更加受社会控制的新凯恩斯主义资本主义中 在这方面 你能给我们一个总体的方向感吗
Do you want me to do it now?
你想我现在就做吗
Yeah, please give it.
是的 请给出
Yeah, but in like five, ten seconds.
是的 但请在五到十秒内
Ha, ha, ha.
哈哈哈
Okay.
好的
In two sentences.
用两句话
We need a Keynesian stabilization just because the free fall is not revolutionary and it It only helps the Nazis.
我们需要凯恩斯主义的稳定 只是因为自由落体不是革命性的 它只会帮助纳粹
The second question.
第二个问题
One stabilization is achieved that buys us breathing ground in order to dream dangerously about the good society.
一旦实现稳定 这给了我们呼吸的空间 去危险地梦想一个好社会
There was another question here, yeah.
这里有另一个问题 是的
Thank you.
谢谢
I'll change the topic back to love and while you were speaking, I was thinking of a movie that brings up this love as a political category.
我会将话题转回爱情 当你在讲话时 我在想一个将爱作为政治范畴的电影
I don't know if you have seen it, this Life of Others, which I think it's a rather stupid movie about this police officer, secret police officer.
我不知道你是否看过它 《窃听风暴》 我认为这是一个相当愚蠢的电影 关于这个秘密警察官员
Oh, you know, okay.
哦 你知道的 好吧
So you know that there is this particular transformation of the secret police officer when he watches the couple being completely in love, making passionate love, and so on and so forth.
所以你知道 当他看着这对情侣完全沉浸在爱中 激情地做爱时 这位秘密警察官员发生了特定的转变
So basically the message is that, okay, once you are exposed, even as a evil secret police officer, once you're exposed to this beautiful miracle of love,
所以基本上的信息是 好的 一旦你 即使作为一个邪恶的秘密警察 一旦你暴露于这种美丽的爱的奇迹
you transform yourself and you basically break with your institution and everyday life rules and you turn good.
你就会转变自己 并基本上与你的机构和日常生活规则决裂 你变得善良
And I was wondering to what extent or where do you draw the line with your own theory of love
我想知道在多大程度上或在哪里你会用你自己的爱的理论
from this bourgeois or if you want modern, modern bourgeois category of love, which is in itself also sort of claiming universal and claiming this particular break with the mundane reality.
与这种资产阶级或如果你愿意的话 现代资产阶级的爱的类别区分开来 这本身也在某种程度上声称是普遍的 并声称与平凡的现实断裂
So what is the particular gift that you...
那么你特别的礼物是什么...
Nice question.
好问题
First, I would say the Stasi officer, he doesn't fall in love.
首先 我会说斯塔西（Stasi）官员 并没有坠入爱河
He falls with a certain, he's an observer.
他以某种观察者的身份坠入了 他是一个观察者
But now, if you permit me, we all know what we are talking about.
但现在 如果你允许的话 我们都知道我们在谈论什么
Lebend are the lives of others, the well-known German film, blah, blah, got the Oscar and so on.
《窃听风暴》 那部著名的德国电影 等等 获得了奥斯卡奖
I think this is, I am also like you totally opposed to this film.
我认为这是 我也像你一样完全反对这部电影
My first reading is that it's almost a modern version of Casablanca.
我的第一印象是它几乎是《卡萨布兰卡》的现代版本
Beneath official topic of heterosexual love,
在异性爱的官方主题之下
it's clearly the final line of the film could have been,
电影的最后一句明显可以是
this is the beginning of a beautiful friendship.
这是一段美好友谊的开始
Between the writer and the Stasi agent,
在作家和斯塔西特工之间
and clearly the woman has to be sacrificed.
很明显女性必须被牺牲
We get rid of the woman, the true couple is created.
我们摆脱了女性 真正的一对才得以形成
Second thing, the movie, that's the paradox.
第二点 电影 这就是悖论
Although the author is ferociously anti-communist.
尽管作者是激烈的反communism者
And a friend of mine in Germany who knows the director, even explained to me why,
我的一个在德国的朋友 他认识导演 甚至向我解释了为什么
he comes with this complicated phone donner schmuck, I don't know what.
他出身于东普鲁士家庭 这个家庭永远不会原谅苏联夺走他们的城堡
He comes from East Prussian family, which never forgave the Soviets to take their castle from them.
不 所以这部电影是一种个人的复仇
No, so this film is a personal revenge.
但讽刺的是 这部电影对警察统治的恐怖还不够严厉
But the irony is that the movie is not harsh enough against the horror of police rule.
你知道为什么吗
What's the hypothesis of the woman?
女性的假设是什么
You know the story.
你知道故事
Young successful writer with a beautiful woman, some high political minister, even whatever, functionary, falls in love with the woman
年轻成功的作家和一个美丽的女人 某个高级政治部长 或者任何官员 爱上了这个女人
and he orders secret police to cover the husband totally, to discover something so that he will get rid of the husband to have the woman.
他命令秘密警察彻底监视丈夫 以发现一些事情 从而摆脱丈夫 拥有这个女人
What a terrible miss, what a terrible falsification.
多么可怕的错失 多么可怕的歪曲
The whole, listen, what happens in this film could have happened in any society.
整个事件 在这部电影中发生的 本可以在任何社会中发生
If you are, if you have a relatively powerful position, a CIA agent can do this, a top executive.
如果你是 如果你处于相对有权势的位置 一个中情局特工可以这么做 一个高级执行官也可以
That is to say, the liberal limit of the film is that it locates evil in one of these private vices.
也就是说 电影届的自由派的局限在于 它将邪恶定位在这些私人恶习上
You want money, you want sex, whatever.
你想要钱 你想要性 无论什么
You do something criminal.
你为此做了某些犯罪行为
But the true horror of Stasi in dead air
但真正的斯塔西恐怖
was the following one.
是下面这种情况
Imagine that there is no wicked minister who wanted,
想象没有那个恶意的部长
if you are the writer, sorry to be personal, imagine there is no secret,
如果你是那位作家 抱歉变得个人化了 想象没有那个想要睡你妻子的高级官僚
there is no high nomenclature guy who wants to fuck your wife.
只有所谓的好警察 像电影中的英雄
There are only, under quotation marks, good policemen like the hero,
你仍然会被监视
And you would still be under observation.
而你仍会被观察
You know, instead of showing how total control was part of this, imagine a writer like the hero of the film, whose plays are performed in the West and so on, it's unimaginable in dead air
你知道 与其展示完全控制是其中的一部分 不如想象一个像电影英雄这样的作家 他的戏剧在西方等地演出 在死气沉沉的空气中 这是不可想象的
that such a person, irrespective of who wants to fuck his wife, would not be under permanent observation.
这样的人 无论谁想睡他的妻子 都不可能不被永久监视
And again, so you see the paradox.
再次 所以你看到了矛盾
This film paints the portrait of horror of dead air,
这部电影描绘了斯塔西时代的恐怖
it's much too modest, which is why,
它过于温和了 这也是为什么
although it's a little bit kitty,
虽然有点俗气
I prefer the other film, Goodbye Lenin, why?
我更喜欢另一部电影 《再见列宁》 为什么呢
Because the fundamental premise embodied in the fate of the mother of that film is that the only way to survive, if you are an honest communist, is that you go crazy, to put it bluntly, no?
因为这部电影中母亲命运所体现的基本前提是 如果你是一个诚实的Communist Party员 唯一的生存方式就是发疯 直白地说 不是吗
It's a, you know, it's not just Ostalgie as they criticized it.
这不仅仅是怀旧 正如人们所批评的那样
But you know, did you see the third film by, I forgot the director, Barbara?
但你知道 你看了第三部电影吗 由我忘了导演 《芭芭拉》
It's a third, a newer film about an East German women doctor being displaced onto some Baltic Sea resort,
这是关于一名东德女医生被调到某个波罗的海度假地的一部较新的电影
falling in love with a local guy who has to report on her, but he's also have this event.
爱上了一个必须向她汇报的当地男人 但他也有这个活动
This is also definitely better film than Lebendorf Anderon, no?
这也绝对是比《窃听风暴》更好的电影 不是吗
I think that was hopefully for us one, how do you call it, one-hit wonder of that guy.
我认为那是给我们的希望 这是那个人的一次成功之作
Didn't he do that phone, whatever, the Prussian cast loner?
他没有拍那个电话 什么的 普鲁士城堡的孤独者吗
Didn't he do some horrible film with Angelina Jolie and Johnny Depp?
他没有和安吉丽娜·朱莉以及约翰尼·德普合作拍摄一部糟糕的电影吗
Sorry?
抱歉
Yeah, didn't he do that one?
是的 他拍了那个吗
And it's horrible, so we are rid of that guy.
而且很糟糕 所以我们摆脱了那个人
So there is another question, yeah.
所以有另一个问题 是的
Hello, I want to ask you about, imagine that everything goes like you say, like the perfect love, the perfect world, the perfect earth, the perfect everything.
你好 我想问你 想象一切都像你说的那样 完美的爱 完美的世界 完美的地球 完美的一切
And what happens next when we are leaving each other and appears our real nature?
当我们离开彼此 我们的真实本性显现时 接下来会发生什么
Real a real nature is like everybody can be an assassin.
真实的本性就像每个人都可能成为杀手
You know.
你知道的
It's like everybody can be like a murder you must just push a button and Our nature is like we are a natural born killers.
就像每个人都可能成为杀手 你只需按下一个按钮 我们的本性就是我们天生的杀手
I wouldn't be no I'm not ideal
我不会 不 我不是理想主义者
No first I would have said that You know I have no great believe in what you call human nature
首先 我要说的是 你知道 我并不真正相信所谓的人性
I always oppose this spontaneous communist idea that if you are for a new, more solid society, that you must somehow believe in essential goodness of humans and so on.
我总是反对这种自发的communism观念 即如果你支持一个新的、更稳固的社会 你必须在某种程度上相信人类的本质善良等等
No, I tend to agree spontaneously.
不 我倾向于自发地同意
Like many intelligent Marxists, like look at Bertolt Brecht.
像许多聪明的马克思主义者一样 看看贝托尔特·布莱希特
He said in a wonderful short text that humans are by nature evil.
他在一篇精彩的短文中说 人类本性是邪恶的
You cannot change humans, you can only change conditions to take from the people possibility to actualize their evil or whatever.
你不能改变人类 你只能改变条件 从人们手中夺走实现其邪恶或其他任何东西的可能性
But on the other hand, you know,
但另一方面 你知道
things are a little bit more complicated.
事情更加复杂一些
When you say we are all natural born killers,
当你说我们都是天生的杀手时
I wouldn't put it like this.
我不会这么说
I would put it like we have maybe a certain propensity for violence, for acting out, which can be put to many different uses.
我会说 我们可能有某种暴力倾向 行动倾向 这可以被用于许多不同的用途
It can be turned into, you know what I mean?
它可以转变成 你知道我的意思吗
The problem, I don't see a great, I don't see a great problem here.
问题是 我不认为这里有大问题
I think, you know, it's the same problem as, for example, if you talk with intelligent geneticists, biologists, and they tell you, all of them, who are real, professional scientists,
我认为 就像如果你和聪明的遗传学家、生物学家交谈时一样 他们会告诉你 所有真正的专业科学家都会说
and they tell me, forget about all that bullshit, we discovered a gene for homosexuality, for jealousy, for religion, it's all bullshit.
忘记那些废话 我们发现了同性恋、嫉妒、宗教的基因 全都是废话
These are very vague tendencies and it turns on the combination with other genes, how they turn out, and it's the same I think with this human nature.
这些都是非常模糊的倾向 取决于与其他基因的组合如何发挥作用 我认为与所谓的人性也是一样的
I doubt that there are, I'm not saying, I never, let me be clear in this way, when I talk about communism and so on, no, I'm not even saying there will be, if there will be a society which will overcome capitalism.
我怀疑 我不是说 我从来不说 让我在这方面说得清楚 当我谈论communism等时 不 我甚至不说如果有一个能够克服资本主义的社会会有更多幸福等等
I'm not even saying there will be more happiness there, and so on, or whatever.
我甚至不说那里会有更少的痛苦等等
Less suffering, and so on, and so on.
我在这里是最残酷的现实主义者
I'm totally the most brutal realist you can imagine here.
最重要的是 我认为我没有使用理想这个词
On the top of it, I think I didn't use the word ideal.
我使用了奇迹这个词
I used the word miracle.
我相信奇迹
I believe in miracles.
我认为生活是糟糕的 但我相信 以一种唯物主义的方式
miracles happen, and that's for me the greatness of ethics.
奇迹发生 这对我来说是伦理的伟大之处
I knew people who were total shit, conformists, and so on,
我认识的人中 有些人完全是垃圾 墨守成规等等
and at some point they say, fuck it, I have it enough.
而在某个时刻他们说 去他的 我受够了
I will not take this, and they become momentarily heroes.
我不会忍受这个 他们变成了瞬间的英雄
A great figure from history for this, Giordano Bruno.
历史上的一个伟大人物 乔丹诺·布鲁诺
We only know about his, you know, how he was burned,
我们只知道他是如何被烧死的
But until that final moment, he was just walking around, slandering, compromising, and so on.
但直到那最后时刻 他只是四处游荡 诽谤 妥协等等
All of a sudden, you have the moment of a miracle.
突然之间 你有了奇迹的时刻
And I read a wonderful similar story of a top German Nazi officer.
我读到了一个德国纳粹高级军官的类似精彩故事
He was not a mega anti-Semite, but he was a pretty nasty guy.
他不是一个极端的反犹太人 但他是个相当讨厌的家伙
He was helping, organizing, Holocaust, blah, blah, blah.
他帮助组织了大屠杀 等等
At a certain point in 43, something broke down in him.
在43年的某个时刻 他内心崩溃了
And he said, no, I cannot go on with this anymore.
他说 不 我不能再这样下去了
And he risked his life to save Jews and so on and so on.
他冒着生命危险去拯救犹太人等等
So no, I don't believe in any good human nature.
所以 不 我不相信任何良好的人性
I believe in miracles.
我相信奇迹
I believe that while life is generally shit,
我相信虽然生活通常很糟糕
things happen here and there.
但这里和那里会发生事情
You know, we all, I don't, you,
你知道 我们所有人 我不 你
we all cheat our wives, our husbands, it's all bullshit.
我们都欺骗我们的妻子 我们的丈夫 这都是废话
Fuck it, once here and there you find Andre Gorbs.
去他的 偶尔在这里和那里你会找到安德烈·戈尔布斯
You know?
你知道吗
And that's enough for me, almost.
这对我来说已经足够了 几乎
I'm very modest.
我非常谦虚
I just need a miracle here and there.
我只需要偶尔一个奇迹
Yeah, since our simultaneous translators are working all the day,
是的 由于我们的同声传译员整天都在工作
and please, a big applause for them as well.
也请为他们热烈鼓掌
I know what they will be doing now.
我知道他们现在会做什么
They will hate me so much for me talking fast
他们会因为我说得太快而非常讨厌我
that immediately they will go home or to a store,
他们会立刻回家或者去商店
buy a voodoo doll of me,
买一个我的巫毒娃娃
and they will be putting needles in, you know,
然后他们会往里面插针 你知道的
to take so that then I will awaken with pains as a revenge.
以便然后我醒来时会感到疼痛 作为报复
And I understand you fully for doing that.
如果你们这么做 我完全理解
But the question is, what did they do translate right now?
但问题是 他们现在翻译得对吗
I hope you did what I once saw when I was young.
我希望你们做的是我年轻时曾经看过的
A wonderful documentary on, you remember if you are old enough, there was Duvalier dictatorship in Haiti.
一部精彩的纪录片 如果你年纪足够大的话 你会记得 海地有杜瓦利埃独裁统治
And then there was baby Duvalier, the stupid son, big fat guy who was a dictator.
然后有了小杜瓦利埃 那个愚蠢的儿子 那个大胖子独裁者
And I saw on TV a press conference with him.
我在电视上看到了他的一个新闻发布会
And a Western journalist asked him, what's the economic situation in Haiti?
一个西方记者问他 海地的经济状况怎么样
And Duvalier just said, well, it's not too bad.
杜瓦利埃只是说 嗯 还不错
And then the translator translated this in view of the recent stock exchange trendings and that theory and so on.
然后翻译将这翻译成考虑到最近的股票市场趋势和那个理论等等
I hope you did the opposite, no?
我希望你做的是相反的 不是吗
I go on for 10 minutes, and you say, he's just bullshitting.
我讲了10分钟 你们说 他只是在胡说八道
He doesn't have a good answer.
他没有一个好回答
So one last question.
所以最后一个问题
Who will it be?
谁来提
If there are no questions?
如果没有问题的话
No, I will be the pseudo-Buddhist or Heideggerian.
不 我会是伪佛教徒或海德格尔主义者
If there are no questions, then you should listen to silence itself as the ultimate answer, you know, and clap with one hand to it, okay?
如果没有问题 那你应该倾听沉默本身作为最终的回答 你知道的 对它鼓掌 好吗
Unfortunately, there is a question without silence.
不幸的是 有一个问题 没有沉默
There's one brief question, I'll try to make it brief.
有一个简短的问题 我会尽量简短
It's about a book written by a young French historian and philosopher, I think her last name is Decree, I bought that book for my mom's birthday,
这是关于一本书 书是由一位年轻的法国历史学家和哲学家写的 我认为她的姓是Decree 我买这本书作为我妈妈的生日礼物
so I haven't read all of it, but I read the main part.
所以我还没读完整本书 但我读了主要部分
Anyway, the main part is about Mussolini as such, and Hitler, which really made quite an impression on me. made quite an impression on me.
无论如何 主要部分是关于墨索里尼本人和希特勒的 这真的给我留下了深刻的印象
My point is they were major leaders, they were seen as strong characters, Il Duce, Der Führer, and all that, whilst when we read their letters to their mistresses.
我的观点是 他们是重要的领导人 被视为强大的人物 Il Duce（元首） Der Führer（领袖） 等等 而当我们读他们写给情妇的信时
They were quite fragile, very unstable, and even there's a letter from Mussolini to one of his mistresses where he says, that is so miserable, poor, doesn't know how to cope, how to manage without her.
他们显得相当脆弱 非常不稳定 甚至有一封墨索里尼写给他其中一位情妇的信 他说 自己是如此痛苦 贫穷 不知道如何应对 没有她怎么办
And there's this notion of love, and yet power,
而这就涉及到爱情的概念 还有权力
which reflects this lack of power in the Lacanian sense, we could say, and how would you comment
这反映了在拉康意义上的权力缺失 我们可以说 你如何评论一个人在一方面是伟大的领袖 在另一方面却是非常软弱的人
has no friends, has numerous mistresses and so on, but he's a person who has no self-confidence.
没有朋友 有许多情妇等等 但他是一个没有自信的人
On the other side, a great leader.
另一方面 却是伟大的领袖
I think I can give you a very brief and precise answer.
我认为我可以给你一个非常简洁和准确的回答
What I don't believe in is that this intimate self-experience is some kind of a deeper truth about that person.
我不相信这种内心自我体验是关于那个人的某种更深层的真相
I think that the truth is outside in what Mussolini was doing.
我认为真相在于墨索里尼的所作所为之外
And I think that this self-image of a vulnerable, fragile person is precisely the lie he invented for himself to be able to do the horrors he was doing publicly out there.
我认为这种脆弱、易碎的自我形象正是他为自己发明的谎言 以便他能够在公众场合做出他所做的恐怖行为
And this goes generally, you know.
这是普遍的 你知道的
I don't think that, because if you approach it in this way, it's not only Hitler and Mussolini.
我不认为 因为如果你以这种方式来看待它 不仅仅是希特勒和墨索里尼
I'm absolutely sure that Stalin played and loved his daughter Svetlana and so on and so on.
我绝对确信斯大林也爱他的女儿斯维特兰娜等等
All dictators or generally men, evil men, the more they are brutal, the more they need some private fetish when they can say, or for example, with big bank managers and so on.
所有独裁者或一般来说的邪恶男人 他们越是残忍 就越需要一些私人的小秘密 当他们可以说 例如 对于大银行经理等人
that the same role is played by private donations and charities.
私人捐赠和慈善活动发挥着相同的作用
You know you're a manager of a big bank brutally destroying lives of 10,000 then in the
你知道 你是一家大银行的经理 残酷地摧毁了一万人的生活
afternoon you say but it's horrible what is happening in Somalia let me give 2%
然后在下午你说 但是发生在索马里的事情太可怕了 让我捐赠我财富的2%给他们 你感觉很好 你可以告诉自己
that's just business that I'm ruining hundreds of thousand this is the true me This fragile person who is ready to cry with you, this is it.
你看 这只是生意 虽然我毁了成千上万的人 但这才是真正的我 这个准备和你一起哭泣的脆弱人物 就是这样
So again, to put it very brutally, I think that we don't lie just to others.
所以再次 非常直白地说 我认为我们不仅仅对别人撒谎
We lie especially to ourselves, and especially when we do horrible things.
我们甚至也会对自己撒谎 特别是当我们做了可怕的事情时
We need, as it were, a private myth, how we present ourselves to others.
我们需要 可以说 一个私人的神话 怎样向别人展示我们自己
My God, this is a dream of a very great man who does horrible things.
我的天 这是一个做了可怕的事情的伟大人物的梦想
To present him celibate, you see, if you were to see me alone, you would see that I'm also a modest person with all the weaknesses and so on and so on.
让他成为独身者 你看 如果你单独看我 你会发现我也是一个谦虚的人 有所有的弱点等等
Which is why I claim that maybe even the fundamental form of ideology today is I'm not just embodiment of economic or ideological categories, I'm also a warm, fragile human person.
这就是为什么我声称 也许今天意识形态的根本形式是 我不仅仅是经济或意识形态范畴的体现 我也是一个温暖、脆弱的人
That's the lie.
那是谎言
That's why I like Brecht, where, in a brutal way, he doesn't allow for that.
这就是为什么我喜欢布莱希特 在一种残酷的方式中 他不允许那样
He precisely reduces capitalists or people to their social roles.
他准确地将资本家或人简化为他们的社会角色
Like, the big rule of Brecht is, please don't come up with that bullshit, what a beautiful, deep, profound, careful person you are privately for yourself, and so on and so on.
布莱希特的重要规则是 请不要拿出那种胡说八道 你私下是多么美好、深刻、细心的人 等等
That's, for me, not even something specifically communist.
对我来说 这甚至不是特别communism的东西
This is what I see even already the great legacy of Jewish ethics.
这是我甚至已经看到的犹太伦理的伟大遗产
It's a totally intersubjective ethics.
这是一种完全互为主体的伦理
It's not, oh, no, no, wait a minute.
不是 哦 不 等一下
I am very critical of, wait a minute,
我对 等一下 我很批判
I am usually accused in Israel of up to preparing a new Holocaust and so on.
在以色列问题上 我经常被指控准备一场新的大屠杀等等
I am part of the boycott there.
我是抵制运动的一部分
So I am not, but my criticism of state of Israel is, I think, more intelligent.
所以我不是 但我对以色列国的批评 我认为 更聪明
What I'm claiming is that the greatest threat to what was great in Jewish identity comes from the state of Israel, the way it works now.
我声称 对犹太身份的伟大威胁来自于现在的以色列国和它的运作方式
If the tendency, if what they are doing now will go on, in one, two generations, Jews will be just another boring colonialist nation like all the other,
如果他们现在的趋势继续下去 一两代人后 犹太人将只是另一个无聊的殖民主义民族 如同所有其他的
all that was great in Jewish tradition, their implicit universality and so on will be lost.
犹太传统中的伟大 他们的内在普遍性等将会丧失
But what I want to say that the greatest of traditional Jewish ethics is the total externalization.
但我想说的是 传统犹太伦理的最伟大之处是完全的外在化
The truth is not, but what did this know?
真相不是 但这是什么知识
The truth is in how you interact with others, not in how did you experience it in your insight, what did it mean to your spiritual growth.
真相在于你如何与他人互动 而不在于你如何在你的内省中体验它 不在于这对你的精神成长意味着什么
I think that all these categories of authentic self-experience, inner spiritual growth, and so on are bullshit.
我认为所有这些关于真实的自我体验、内在精神成长等类别都是胡说八道
I believe in total externality.
我相信完全的外在性
To give you another from my old books example,
给你另一个来自我旧书的例子
my favorite story about ethics is how it was told by an old black friend for me from South Africa.
我最喜欢的关于伦理的故事是一位来自南非的老黑人朋友告诉我的
In the old days of apartheid, a policeman was dispersing a black demonstration.
在种族隔离的旧日子里 一名警察在驱散一个黑人示威
And one policeman was running after,
一个警察在追赶 一个试图逃跑的黑人女士 可能是中产阶级 穿着高跟鞋等等
Then something weird happened.
然后发生了一件奇怪的事
Trying to run away with high-heeled shoes, which doesn't work well, made the lady drop.
她试图穿着高跟鞋逃跑 这行不通 使得这位女士跌倒了
She lost one shoe.
她丢了一只鞋
And at that point, the policeman, and I must emphasize this, it's not that he was inherently a good person or what, but this totally superficial manners took over.
这时 警察 我必须强调 不是因为他内心本就是一个好人 而是这种完全表面的礼貌占了上风
When you see a lady in distress, and she stopped, took the shoe, and give it to him, here it is, lady.
当你看到一位处于困境的女士时 他停下来 拾起鞋子 递给她 给你 女士
And then they looked at each other, and they felt stupid.
然后他们相互看了看 感到很傻
Like, now that she has the shoes on, what's she to do?
好吧 既然她穿上了鞋子 她该怎么办
OK, now we start running again.
好的 我们现在再次开始跑吗
So embarrassed, he said, goodbye, lady, and turned around and walked away.
尴尬地 他说 再见 女士 然后转身走开了
That's the morality I believe in.
这就是我相信的道德
I'm not making the point, that's crucial, that this black policeman was deep in his heart a good person.
我要强调的是 并不是说这位黑人警察在心底是个好人
No, deep in his heart he was probably a shitty racist and so on.
不 他在心底可能是个彻头彻尾的种族主义者
But you know, superficial manners can do miracles.
但你知道 表面的礼貌可以创造奇迹
You do this 10 times, and maybe your deep, deep heart will change a little bit.
你这么做10次 也许你深深的内心会有所改变
This is, for me, the greatest case of Mark Twain, I think, in Huck Finn.
这对我来说 是马克·吐温在《哈克贝里·费恩历险记》中的最佳案例
There is a legendary scene where I think that Huck or Tom Sarnon, who they help a runaway black slave, and then they feel morally bad for doing something.
有一个传奇场景 我认为是哈克或汤姆·索亚 他们帮助一个逃跑的黑奴 然后他们因为做了某件事而感到道德上的不安
You know how what they did externally was right, but precisely their inner bad feeling is what is non-authentic.
你知道他们表面上做的事情是对的 但是他们内心的不好的感觉却是不真实的
Like how they are not racist on the outside.
就像他们表面上没有种族主义一样
On the outside, they did a different thing.
外在 他们做了不同的事
On the inside, they are racist, which is why, again, I
内在 他们是种族主义者 这就是为什么 再次
believe in surfaces, in good manners.
我相信表面 相信良好的礼仪
I don't believe in that.
我不相信那个
I don't believe in really loving others.
我不相信真正地爱他人
I hate this idea of we should love other races, other nations.
我讨厌我们应该爱其他种族 其他国家的这个想法
No, we should hate them.
不 我们应该讨厌他们
We should just learn to pretend to act as if we care for them
我们应该学会假装 表现得好像我们关心他们
and to be in this way to maintain appropriate distance and so on.
以这种方式保持适当的距离等等
I think that the most disgusting motto
我认为最恶心的座右铭
is this politically correct one, do we know others enough?
是这个政治正确的 我们了解其他人吗
We should get to know them.
我们应该去了解他们
No, I think people are boring.
不 我认为人们是无聊的
I don't want to know too many things about them.
我不想知道太多关于他们的事情
It's quite enough to have a respectful distance.
保持尊重的距离就足够了
This idea, we should know the other.
这个想法 我们应该了解其他人
How can we know the other when the others don't know themselves?
当其他人都不了解自己时 我们怎么能了解其他人呢
I mean, you know what I mean.
我的意思是 你知道我的意思
I believe in superficial manners.
我相信表面的礼貌
I saw that the applause was not to warn.
我看到掌声不是为了警告
It's okay.
没关系
When we communists will take power, and you will learn how to do it.
当我们Communist Party人掌权时 你们会学会如何做
OK, a bigger applause, please.
好的 请大声鼓掌
No, no.
不 不用
Love is over.
爱情结束了
I divorce you now.
我现在和你离婚